Hi. So I was trying this experiment of making really short videos, and I thought,
oh, this is nice. I'll be able to put them out simultaneously on TikTok and YouTube Shorts,
which some other creators have been doing. So I recorded this video, it's like two and a bit
minutes long, and uploaded it to TikTok. And then I realized that YouTube Shorts
only allows one minute video. You don't care. Here's the video.
Hey, did you hear about this? This is GitHub Copilot. It's an AI system that writes code.
You just give it an English description of what you want the code to do, and it writes it. It's
pretty good. But what can this tell us about why future AI systems might be dangerous?
Hi, I'm Rob Miles. I make videos about AI safety. So in the field of AI safety,
we have this concept of alignment, which is about are the AI system's goals aligned with ours? Is
it trying to do what we want it to do? See, when you have an AI system which is doing the wrong
thing, there's kind of two reasons why that might happen. One of them is a capability problem. Maybe
the system just isn't smart enough, isn't capable enough to know how to do the right thing.
The other possibility is an alignment problem. That happens when the system knows perfectly well
how to do the right thing, but just doesn't want to. Capability problems tend to sort of
solve themselves in the course of normal AI research. You get more and better data,
you get bigger models, and eventually the system becomes more capable.
But alignment problems are a little bit more tricky. Just making the system more capable
doesn't solve the problem. It actually kind of makes it worse. If you have a very capable system
which is trying to do something that you don't want it to do, that could be really dangerous.
So what would it mean for a system that writes code to be misaligned? Well, what we want is for
it to write good code. So if we find a situation where it writes bad code, but where it does
actually know how to write that code well, then that's an indication of misalignment. So by that
definition, is GitHub Copilot misaligned? The answer to this and many other questions is yes.
This recent paper had a look and found exactly that. See, Codex, the model on which Copilot
is based, is not actually trying to write good code. It's trying to predict what comes next. And
this means that if you've written some bad code, and then you ask the model to carry on and write
the next part of the code, it will carry on with bad code. If you write buggy code, it will continue
with buggy code. If you write insecure code, it will introduce security vulnerabilities. And we
know it's not a capabilities problem, because if you write good code, it will complete with good
code. So it doesn't know how to write good code. It's just choosing not to, because that's just not
what it's trying to do. It's misaligned. And we shouldn't just expect this problem to go away with
bigger models and more data. In fact, they tested this with a range of different model sizes, and
they found that the larger models do this more. Because they're better at spotting more subtle
patterns, they're able to better spot the difference between good code and bad code.
They're able to spot the subtle bugs and notice that the code completions should also have subtle
bugs. So this alignment problem is going to become increasingly central to the development of AI.
The question stops being, does our AI system know how to do the right thing?
And becomes, does our AI system want to do the right thing?