Right, hello everyone. My name is Robert Miles. I am usually doing this on YouTube. I'm not
really used to public speaking. I'm not used to not being able to edit out my mistakes.
There may be mistakes. Also, I may go too quickly. Sorry, not sorry. So, when it comes
to AI safety, you can kind of divide it up into four areas along two axes. You've got
your short-term and your long-term, and you've got accident risks and misuse risks. And that's
kind of a useful way to divide things up. AI safety covers everything. The area that
interests me most is the long-term accident risks. I think once you have very powerful
AI systems, it almost doesn't matter if they're being used by the right people or the wrong
people or what you're trying to do with them. The difficulty is in keeping them under control
at all. So that's what I'm going to be talking about. What is AI safety? Why is it important?
So I want to start by asking the question which I think everybody needs to be asking
themselves. What is the most important problem in your field? Take a second to think of it.
Why are you not working on that? For me, I think the most important problem in the field
of AI is AI safety. This is the problem specifically that I'm worried about. That we will sooner
or later build an artificial agent with general intelligence. So I'm going to go into a bunch
of these terms. The first thing is, what do I mean when I say sooner or later? This is
a little bit washed out, but this is a graph of a large survey of AI experts. These are
people who published in major AI conferences, and they were asked when they thought we would
achieve high-level machine intelligence, which is defined as an agent which is able to carry
out any task humans can as well as or better than humans. They say that a 50% chance of
having achieved that, we hit that about 45 years from 2016. But then, of course, we hit
like 10% chance nine years from now. So it's not immediate, but it's happening. This is
definitely worth taking with a pinch of salt because if you ask the question slightly differently,
you get an estimate of 120 years rather than 45. There's a lot of uncertainty in this area.
But the point is, it's going to happen, as I said, sooner or later. Because at the end of the day,
general intelligence is possible. The brain implements it, and the brain is not magic.
Sooner or later, we'll figure it out. So what do I mean when I say an artificial agent?
Well, so an agent is a term from economics, mostly. But basically, agents have goals.
They choose actions to further their goals is the simplest expression of what an agent is.
So the simplest thing that you might call an agent would be something like a thermostat.
It has a goal, which is to have the room be at a particular temperature. It has actions it can
take. It can turn on the heating. It can turn on the air conditioning. It chooses its actions to
achieve its goal of maintaining the room at a steady temperature. Extremely simple agent.
A more complex agent might be something like a chess AI, which has a goal of, if it's playing
white, it has a goal of the black king being in checkmate. And it takes actions in the form of
moving pieces on the board in order to achieve its goal. So you see how this idea of an agent
is a very useful way of thinking about lots of different intelligence systems. And of course,
humans can be modeled as agents as well. This is how it's usually done in economics.
Individuals or companies could be considered to have a goal of maximizing their income
or maximizing their profits and making decisions in order to achieve that.
So when I'm talking about intelligence,
intelligence has a lot of, as a term, is a heavily loaded term, has a lot of different
people put their own definitions on it. In this context, what I mean when I say intelligence is
just the thing that lets an agent choose effective actions. It's whatever it is that's in our brains
or that's in the programming of these systems that means that the actions they choose tend to
get them closer to their goals. And so then you could say that an agent is more intelligent if
it's more effective at achieving its goals, whatever those goals are. If you have two
agents in an environment with incompatible goals, like let's say the environment is the chess board
and one agent wants white to win and one agent wants black to win, then generally the more
intelligent agent will be the one that gets what it wants. The better AI will win the chess game.
And finally, general intelligence. This is where it becomes interesting in my opinion. So generality
is the ability to behave intelligently in a wide range of domains. If you take something like a
chess AI, it's extremely narrow. It only knows how to play chess. And even though you might say that
it's more intelligent than a thermostat because it's more sophisticated, it's more complicated,
it couldn't do the thermostat's job. There's no position on the chess board that corresponds to
the room being a good temperature. There's no move that corresponds to turning on an air
conditioner. The chess AI can only think in terms of chess. It's extremely narrow.
Generality is a continuous spectrum. So if you write a program that can play an Atari game,
that's very narrow. DeepMind, one of their early triumphs was that they made a program that could
play dozens of different Atari games. A single program that could learn all of these different
games. And so it's more general because it's able to act across a wider variety of domains.
The most general intelligence that we're aware of right now is human beings. Human beings are
very general. We're able to operate across a very wide range of domains, including,
and this is important, we're able to learn domains which evolution did not and could not prepare us
for. We can, for example, drive a car. And evolution did not prepare us for that. We invented cars.
They're very recent. We can, you know, invent rockets and go to the moon. And then we can
operate on the moon, which is a completely different environment. And this is kind of
the power of general intelligence. Really, the power of general intelligence is,
we can build a car, we can build a rocket, we can put the car on the rocket, take the car to the
moon, drive the car on the moon. And there's nothing else that can do that yet. But sooner
or later, right? So this is what I'm talking about. I'm talking about what you might call true AI,
real AI, the sci-fi stuff. An agent which has goals in the real world and is able to intelligently
choose actions in the real world to achieve those goals. Now that sounds, I've said, I've said,
what's the biggest problem? This doesn't sound like a problem, right? On the surface of it,
this sounds like a solution. You just tell the thing, you know, cure cancer or maximize the
profits of my company or whatever. And it takes whatever actions are necessary in the real world
to achieve that goal. But it is a problem. So the big problem is, this should be auto playing,
and it isn't. The big problem is, it's difficult to choose good goals. So this is an AI made by
OpenAI. It's playing a game called Coast Runners, which is actually a racing game.
They trained it on the score, which you probably can't see down here. It's currently a thousand.
What the system learned is that if it goes around in a circle here and crashes into everything and
catches fire, these little turbo pickups, they respawn at just the right rate that if it just
flings itself around in a circle, it can pick up the turbo. And that gives you a few points every
time you do that. And it turns out that this is a much better way of getting points than actually
racing around the track. And the important point here is that this is not unusual. This is not
OpenAI doing anything unusually stupid. This is kind of the default. Picking objectives is
surprisingly hard. And you will find that the strategy or the behavior that maximizes your
objective is probably not the thing you thought it was. It's probably not what you were aiming for.
There's loads of examples. Actually, Victoria has a great list on her blog,
Deep Safety. There's like 30 of them, different things going wrong. There was one they had,
they were trying to teach, they were trying to evolve systems that would run quickly. So,
they trained them on the, I'm going to pause this because it's distracting as hell.
They were training agents that were supposed to run. So, they simulated them for a particular
period of time and measured how far their center of mass moved, which seems perfectly sensible.
What they found was that they developed a bunch of these creatures, which were extremely tall
and thin with a big mass on the end, that then fell over. Because they weren't simulating them
for long enough that you could go the fastest just by falling over rather than actually running.
That moved your center of mass the furthest. There's a lot of these. There was a Tetris bot
which would play reasonably well, and then just when it was about to lose, would pause the game
and sit there indefinitely. Because it lost points for losing, but didn't lose any points
for just sitting on the pause screen indefinitely. This is like the default of how these systems
behave. I have no memory what my next slide is. Oh, yeah, right. So, okay. So, now we're getting
into why is this like a computer science problem? This is a quote from Stuart Russell, who sort of
wrote the book on AI. When a system is optimizing a function of n variables where the objective
depends on a subset of size k, which is less than n, it will often set the remaining unconstrained
variables to extreme values. If one of those unconstrained variables is something that we care
about, the solution found may be highly undesirable. So, let me break this down. Suppose you've got,
you've built a general AI. It's like a robot, and you've created it with a goal, and you've given it
a simple goal. You know, a big part of the issue, I remember how I was supposed to come into this
slide. We have problems specifying even simple goals in simple environments, like Atari games,
or basic evolutionary algorithms, things like that. When it comes to the real world,
things get way more complicated. And so, we're talking about very large values for n here.
In the real world, we have a very large number of variables. So, let's say you've got your robot,
and you've given it a goal which you think is very simple. You want it to get you a cup of tea.
So, you've managed to specify what a cup of tea is, and that you want one to be on the desk in
front of you. So far, so good. But, suppose there is a there's a priceless Ming vase on a narrow
stand, sort of in front of where the kitchen is. So, the robot immediately plows into the vase and
destroys it on its way to make you a cup of tea, because you only gave it one variable to keep
track of in the goal, which is the tea. It doesn't care about the vase. You never told it to care
about the vase. It destroys the vase. This is a problem. So, okay, now you can, you know, shut it
down, modify it, and say, okay, get me a cup of tea, but also don't knock over the vase. But then,
there will be a third thing. There is always another thing, because when you're making
decisions in the real world, you're always making trade-offs. You're always taking various things
that you value and deciding how much of one you're willing to trade for how much of another.
You know, I could do this quicker, but it increases the risk of me making a mistake. Or, I could do this
cheaper, but it won't be as reliable. I could do this faster, but it'll be more expensive.
You're always trading these things off against one another. And so, an agent like this, which
only cares about a limited subset of the variables in the system, will be willing to trade off
arbitrarily large amounts of any of the variables that aren't part of its goal for arbitrarily tiny
increases in any of the things which are in its goal. So, it will happily, let's say now, for
example, now it values the vase, and those are the only things that it values. It might reason something
like, okay, there's a human in the environment. The human moves around. The human may accidentally
knock over the vase, and I care about the vase, so I have to kill the human, right? And this is totally
ridiculous, but if you didn't tell it that you value being alive, it doesn't care, and anything
that it doesn't value is going to be lost. If you manage to come up with, if you have a sufficiently
powerful agent, and you manage to come up with a really good objective function which covers
the top 20 things that humans value, the 21st thing that humans value is probably gone forever,
because the smarter, the more powerful the agent is, the better it will be at figuring out ways to
make these trade-offs, to gain a millionth of a percent better at one thing, while sacrificing
everything of some other variable. So, this is a problem, but actually that scenario I gave was
unrealistic in many ways, but one important way that it was unrealistic is that I had the
system go wrong, and then you just turn it off and fix it, but in fact, if the thing has
a goal of getting you a cup of tea, this is not like a chess AI, where you can just turn it off
because it has no concept of itself or of being turned off. Its world model contains you, it
contains itself, it contains the possibility of being turned off, and it's fully aware that
if you turn it off because it knocked over the vase, it won't be able to get you any tea, which
is the only thing it cares about. So, it's not going to just let you turn it off, it will fight you,
or if it's slightly smarter, it will deceive you so that you believe it's working correctly,
so that you don't want to change it until it's in a position where you can't turn it off,
and then it will go after its actual objective.
So, this is a problem, and the thing is, this is a convergent instrumental goal,
which means it sort of doesn't matter what the goal is, it doesn't matter what your goal is as
an agent. If you're destroyed, you can't achieve that goal, so it sort of almost doesn't matter
what goal we give it. There is only a very tiny fraction of possible goals that will involve it
actually allowing itself to be turned off and modified, and that's quite complicated.
There are some other convergent instrumental goals. So, we had self-preservation, goal
preservation, resource acquisition is the kind of thing we can expect these kinds of systems to do.
Most plans, you can do them better if you have more resources, whether that's money,
computational resources, just free energy, matter, whatever.
The other one is self-improvement. Whatever you're trying to do, you can probably do it
better if you're smarter, and AI systems potentially have the capacity to improve themselves, either
just by acquiring more hardware to run on, or changing, you know, improving their software
to run faster or better, or so on. So, there's a whole bunch of behaviors which intelligent systems,
intelligent agents, generally intelligent agents, we would expect them to do by default,
and that's really my core point. Artificial general intelligence is dangerous by default.
It's much, much easier to build these kinds of agents which try to do ridiculous things,
and trick you, and try to deceive you, or will fight you when you try to turn them off, or modify them,
on the way to doing some ridiculous thing which you don't want.
Much easier to build that kind of agent than it is to build something which actually reliably does
what you want it to do, and that's why we have a problem, because we have 45 to 120 years
to figure out how to do it safely, which is a much harder problem, and we may only get one shot.
It's entirely possible that the first true artificial general intelligence will manage to
successfully achieve whatever its stupid goal is, and that could be truly a disaster on a global scale.
So we have to defeat, we have to, we have to beat this challenge on hard mode before anyone
beats it on easy mode. So are we screwed? No, we're only probably screwed. There are
things we can do. Safe general artificial intelligence is totally possible, it's just a
very difficult technical challenge, and there are people working very hard on it right now, trying to
solve a whole range of difficult technical challenges so that we can figure out how to do this safely.
Thanks.