When I was a boy, our Nintendo Was cut from an old apple tree
And we used garden hose to connect it To our steam-powered Comma TV
But it still beat that ancient Atari
Cos I damn near went blind, don't you know?
Playing Breakout and Pop on a video game Hooked up to the radio
And we walked seven miles in a schoolhouse
Barefoot and a hill both ways
Through blizzards in summer and winter
Back in the good old days
Back when Fortran was not even 3-tran
And a PC was only a toy
We did our computing by gaslight
When I was a boy
When I was a boy on that twilight sea
People hauling in fish from the sea
Our board range was 8 bits an hour
And our IP address was 3
And you kids who complain that your mobile network's too slow
Ought to cut out your bitchin'
Cos when I was a boy, every packet
Was delivered by carrier pigeon
And we walked 15 miles in a schoolhouse
Barefoot and a hill both ways
Through blizzards in summer and winter
Back in the good old days
Back when Fortran was not even 2-tran
And the mainframe was only a toy
And we did our computing by torchlight
When I was a boy
When I was a boy, our I.S. showed
The relational tables were weird
And we wrapped our data in oilcloth
Preserving the best that we could
And we carried our bits in a bucket
And our mainframe weighed 900 tonnes
And we programmed in 1s and in 0s
And sometimes we ran out of 1s
And we walked 30 miles to the schoolhouse
Barefoot and a hill both ways
Through blizzards in summer and winter
Back in the good old days
Back when Fortran was not even 1-tran
And the abacus only a toy
And we did our computing in primordial darkness
When I was a boy