So there's a thing that I see people routinely fail to get and it's a little hard to express.
I'm just going to try.
There's no rule which says that we make it. There's no rule which says that humanity has
to survive this century or even this decade. There's no rule that says that everything's
going to be okay. And when I say this to people, they generally accept it.
Most of the people I talk to, anyway. They say, yeah, of course. Of course,
there's no rule that says that we have to make it. Of course,
humanity could fail. We could go extinct. You know, it could happen.
It's like they know it, but they don't feel it.
They don't take it seriously as an actual possibility. They kind of think,
okay, we have these things that we have to do. We have these challenges we have to overcome.
And so we'll do that. You know, we'll rise to the occasion. We'll figure out what we need to do
and we'll do it. But, okay, this is a related concept. There's no rule which says that the
challenges we're faced with are challenges that we are capable of meeting. Think about something
like an asteroid strike. If a big enough asteroid hits Earth, we're pretty much done for, right?
And I'm not saying that this is something we should day-to-day be concerned about because
we're dealing with geological periods of time, right? Regularly asteroids hit Earth.
We're sort of due for one. But what does that really mean?
Sometime in the next million years or whatever it is. So we have more pressing concerns. But
when people are prepared to take seriously the possibility of an asteroid strike,
usually it's because they're thinking about it like, oh, interesting. Okay, so we have good
telescopes. We would spot the thing. I wonder how long we would have. Would that be enough warning?
Would that be enough time for us to build whatever it is that we needed to build to
go up there and redirect it or blow it up or whatever? So they're willing to think about
the possibility from the perspective of tackling the challenge. But the thing is, as I said,
the periods of time that pass between asteroid strikes are so large that human-scale time
periods don't really matter. The chance of an asteroid strike 200 years from now is more or
less the same as it is now. And similarly, the chance of an asteroid strike 200 years ago is
about the same as it is now. And if you go back a few hundred years, the question becomes very
different. Could we see the asteroid coming? Maybe. Could we do anything about it? No. I mean,
pretty much just flatly no. We didn't have the technology. We didn't have the understanding of
the thing necessary to build something that could deal with that. If an asteroid were headed for
Earth a few hundred years ago, that would just be it. Just game over. Humanity's done. Shame.
You know, you didn't quite develop your technology fast enough to have anything that could
deal with asteroids before one happened to hit you. Oh, well. There is no rule
which says that the challenges the universe faces us with are challenges we can face.
And I hope that kind of gives some taste of what I'm talking about, of like understanding
the possibility that we could be currently faced with challenges that we will not rise to.
That we actually could fail. But people just have a very hard time taking seriously the
possibility that we could fail. I think it comes from a few different places.
One place, obviously, is religion, right? If we were created deliberately by the creator of the
universe, we are important in the universe. And so we're not going to be wiped out by some asteroid.
Or whatever. We're not going to be wiped out in some boring way.
Religions, they're often okay with the idea of an apocalypse, of humanity or of the world ending.
But they're not okay with an accidental apocalypse. They have a very hard time
taking that kind of thing seriously. In a religious apocalypse, it's always part of the plan.
And so someone with a religious mindset, when faced with a scenario in which
humanity is wiped out in a way which is not part of the plan, they have a very hard time
taking that seriously. And I would posit that anyone raised in a society that's primarily
religious probably has a lot of this as well. A lot of this kind of feeling that
maybe we face very difficult challenges, but we'll deal with them. And if we don't,
then that's okay. Because it's all part of the plan. Even if they would not explicitly endorse
this idea, even if they claim to recognize the reality that there is no plan, I think those
lingering ideas don't just immediately disappear when you give up on the supernatural parts of your
religious beliefs and your upbringing. And it's not just capital R religion either, right?
Like anyone who believes that human beings have souls or that human beings are in some way special,
like fundamentally special, that the universe itself has a separate category for human beings.
Because again, there's this sense in which the universe on some level
cares about us, or even just recognizes us, or knows us. And it's not just about us.
It even just recognizes us or acknowledges us as a thing. And if you believe that, again, it's difficult to think about
situations in which we're wiped out in some boring way, with no dramatic final test,
you know, no heroic last stands, no judgments, no thrilling story to tell,
and nobody to tell it to.
So religion is one place that I think this comes from. The other place that it comes from, I think, is fiction,
especially Hollywood, and especially science fiction. And I'm not saying that people can't
tell the difference between fiction and reality. I'm kind of saying that. I mean, on a conscious
level, people can tell the difference between fiction and reality. But I think on some level,
it's like people understand that whatever this fictional thing is, it didn't happen to us.
It didn't happen here on Earth. But it sort of happened somewhere. It happened in the world of
the story. And that still feels real. It's kind of like, say you have two people, A and B. And
person A says, you know, alcohol is actually a really harmful drug. I think we should ban alcohol
in the UK. And person B might reply, well, they did try banning alcohol in the USA in the 1920s, and
that didn't really work out at all the way they hoped it would. And person A would reply, well,
yeah, but that was a different time. It was a different place. You know, modern Britain is
very different from 1920s America, and we could implement it differently, and so on.
And person B would say, yeah, I mean, maybe there are important differences. But still,
the fact that something similar was tried and failed is evidence against the idea, right?
That's useful information to take into consideration. And that doesn't seem like an
unreasonable position to take. But then people would do the same thing, where somebody expresses
something about AI. And somebody else says, yeah, but think about what happened in 2001 A Space
Odyssey or iRobot or something. And you say to them, well, that was fiction. That didn't happen,
right? That's a fictional example. It's different from the real world. It doesn't really make sense
to use that. And they'll say, oh, I know. I know that it's fictional. But still,
there's some sense in which this is like evidence, right? And no, it's not. I mean, it's
at best, it's one dude's best guess. And usually, it's not even that. Because
usually, the person is not trying to be as accurate as possible. They're trying to be entertaining.
So clearly, fiction affects the way people think about this.
It's interesting. It seems like it increases the probabilities people assign to bad things
happening with AI. But it also decreases the probabilities they assign to really,
really bad things happening with AI. In the sense that they have, in some part of their mind,
a whole bunch of examples in which bad things happened. But then we were able to overcome them,
right? And this is not just with AI. This is any existential risk. Even asteroids, for example.
Coming back to them. Even though people often won't explicitly endorse this idea,
I think there's a part of people which says, oh, well, I've seen the world threatened hundreds of
times, right? And every time, it works out. There's some, there's a brave hero or a plucky
band of misfits or something comes along. We figure out what we need to do, and then we do it.
And I guess that's where we are, you know? And some of those people are even potentially helpful
because they offer to join your plucky band of misfits. But they're still not able to take
seriously the possibility that we might lose. Because they've never seen that happen, right?
I mean, they've never seen it happen in fiction or very rarely seen it happen in fiction.
And furthermore, they've never seen it happen in reality, obviously. That's kind of a difficult
one because I feel like you should be able to use reality as evidence. But I mean, of course,
we've never observed humanity being wiped out. Wouldn't be here talking about it if we had.
And so, it's hard to get people to really feel the reality of the situation.
Which is that we, the whole of humanity, we are up here on this tightrope.
We've had no practice, no dry run, no rehearsal. We get one shot and there is no parachute.
There's no safety net. There is no rule that says that we have to make it. We absolutely can fail.
And we will if we don't successfully tackle a series of hard problems.
And there's no rule that says that we're actually capable of tackling those problems.
And there's no rule that says that we have enough time to do so. So we better get to work.