Hi everyone. So today we're trying something a little bit different, because I read that there's recently been released a mod for the Civilization games, which includes AI as an available technology.
So they've changed the game so that you can actually produce super intelligent AI. Looks really interesting.
And this has actually come from the Center for the Study of Existential Risk at the University of Cambridge.
The Verge has a nice interview. I'll put a link to this in the description. A nice interview with Dr. Shahravin, who is the researcher who's managing the project.
And yeah, so I thought what we do for this video is have a kind of a let's play.
I'm new to making let's plays, and I'm actually kind of new to playing Civilization as well. I didn't play it as a kid.
So I've got a friend to come and help me with installing it and configure it and everything like that.
It's Dr. Shahravin from the Center for the Study of Existential Risk.
Good to be here.
That was silly, but I like it.
Okay, so I've got Steam here. I've installed Civ V.
Which version of Civ V?
The regular one.
Just the base game, or vanilla as we call it.
Vanilla, the vanilla one.
So how do I install this mod?
So you need to go into the Steam workshop.
Browse the workshop link.
And then, I mean, we're kind of lucky that we're quite popular at the moment.
So you can click on Super Intelligence.
That's us. That's the Caesar logo.
This version is for people who have the Brave New World expansion.
But that's not what you have, so you can scroll down, and there is a link.
That's the one.
We'll take it to the vanilla version.
With the basic game. Okay, cool.
And then you just hit subscribe.
Okay, so let's play.
Okay, so my understanding of this game is you start from the Stone Age or something.
You start at the prehistory, beginning of humanity type thing, and you work your way up.
So this mod presumably only actually has an effect towards the end of the game, right?
Yes, and we even say in the mod description that we recommend
if you're just trying to take a taste of the mod,
then you should start in the latest age, just before the thing kicks in,
which for vanilla would be in the modern era.
So we're going to show how to do that.
Yeah.
So you need to go into Mods.
Mods.
Yeah, that's fine.
No mods installed.
And there it is.
There it is.
So it's synced from the web.
You just need to click the V.
Enable.
Okay, that's it.
Next.
I want to be...
Who do you want to be?
I think we should be England.
We should be the UK.
Who's that?
You just passed her.
It's Elizabeth.
Did I?
Oh, yeah, right.
Cool.
That's us.
Here we are.
Game era.
You want to change that to modern.
Modern.
So future, you would have already discovered everything AI related,
and that wouldn't be very much fun.
Gotcha.
But starting in modern is the way to do this here.
Uh-huh.
I'm really nervous now, because usually people, when they watch a Let's Play,
they want to watch someone who's, like, really good at the game win the game.
And I don't know what I'm doing at all.
And I think it's going to be terrible.
Oh.
And I hope people are okay with watching me fail to save the world from rogue super intelligence.
Because that's probably what's going to happen.
Right?
This stone is also good for production, but I think at this point not as important.
Only one military unit.
Bloody hell.
Yeah, I figured that stuff out.
I figured that stuff out.
Thank you.
Okay.
I actually have a guy here.
A city.
So I'm okay.
Okay.
Go over and say hi.
It's Almati.
They give us 30 gold.
Thanks, man.
So bad.
They gave me 30 gold.
I can't even, I don't even know how to pronounce the name of their city.
So these are the things that we can currently research.
Yep.
And if you look a little bit into the future, you can see all of the stuff we added.
So this is a new one?
Yep.
And.
Machine learning.
Okay.
So.
And of course.
We keep going.
This one over here.
Ah, the orthogonality thesis.
Nice.
Which was my last video.
So that's good.
It allows you to build the AI safety lab to reduce the chances of rogue super intelligence
eliminating the human race.
Wouldn't that be nice?
Yeah, that sounds great.
Okay.
So the settlers are going to establish the city here.
It's Nottingham.
Hey.
Oh, I see.
We've built Nottingham and now we're unhappy.
Well.
Social policies get us more out of more happiness from universities than we would otherwise get.
Right?
Yeah.
That's already embodied here.
So universities don't usually give you a plus one happiness.
Really?
Maybe they should.
No, I have to do it.
I have to build Nottingham University and I can build a computer file and then my own
channel and it's going to be great.
It's Dublin.
Hey.
Dublin are militaristic, but friendly.
I don't have any comment about that.
It's Tyre.
They're militaristic and irrational.
This city state as well.
It's Belgrade.
Oh, well, okay.
I got the other one wrong as well.
Again, militaristic, but friendly.
Everyone is so militaristic.
Oh.
Hi.
Why is he terrible?
I don't know.
I've heard him called Alexander the Great.
If it's the same guy.
I think it is the same guy.
Maybe this is his cousin.
Okay, so horses.
I guess we don't have horses or any horses nearby any of our cities right now.
True.
Though, admittedly, we're all also in the modern era.
So we don't really care about horses.
They have become obsolete.
Like humans will soon become.
Right.
Yeah.
I keep forgetting that.
So what is this guy doing?
Is he cosplaying?
I don't know.
What kind of creature are you?
I mean, right back at you, Montezuma.
He's got the crazy eyes.
Also the crazy head.
Yeah.
Crazy hat.
I mean, I like his hat.
I have no criticism whatsoever about the hat.
Montezuma the Terrible.
Everybody is terrible.
I mean, you look at his decor.
The thing I like is that he's friendly.
I would hate to see him when he's pissed off.
I'm going to move him like around here so I can just see more.
I've discovered the Grand Mesa.
Grand Mesa.
Yay.
And now we're actually happy.
Everybody's pleased about this big rock.
Good.
Wait, hang on.
Let me have a look at it.
Wow, it's a pretty big rock.
Say hi.
Oh!
It's America.
It's taking a while to load.
No?
Doge Washington.
Okay.
It's his earnest hope that our two people can live side-by-side in peace and prosperity.
That sounds good.
I'd share that hope.
Yeah.
Oh, sugar for cotton.
One for one.
Happy with that.
Yeah, it gives you more happiness.
Sugar is a luxury.
Happiness is good.
We need that to put in our tea.
We are the British.
Perfect.
Yeah.
They really should make tea as a resource.
There's probably a mod that does that.
Tea?
You can't grow tea?
No.
This game is just a fraud.
So, in order to be successful in AI in the late game, what are good things for a civilization to have?
So, first of all, you want to make sure that there is enough safety.
AI safety research is being done.
It requires AI safety labs, and you can only have one per city.
Right.
So, having a fair number of cities is not bad.
Ah, okay.
That makes sense.
Having a bunch of alliances with city-states gives you access to their AI research, which is not bad.
Oh, okay.
Yep, that makes sense.
So, if there are safety researchers in Dublin and we're friends with them, we can use their safety research.
Yep.
And their capabilities research as well.
Oh, okay.
Of course, you want to have a good science base, so you discover all the technologies that speed up your research.
So, you know how citizens get made.
How do citizens get made?
I mean, are we going to get into it?
Well, yes, but really what happens is you have lots of apples, and then your little circle gets full of apples, and then those apples turn into a citizen.
Oh, okay.
And then your circle gets emptied of all the apples, and you need to start over again.
Yeah, that's pretty much how I remember it from biology.
So, we met a skier.
Hi, skier.
Are you aware that your city is on fire?
Maybe you should attend to that first.
Or is this somebody else's city?
I mean, they do get triple gold from pillaging cities.
Right.
So, that's probably someone else's city.
Okay.
Yeah, you don't shrink from war when necessary.
Or fun.
Or expedient.
Okay.
Again, friendly.
Not really seeing it.
Oh.
And he was friendly.
He was friendly.
You know, I said I had a bad feeling about him.
Must be all these skulls.
So, I get to choose between saying, you'll pay for this in time, or very well.
Which do you think is more British?
I mean, the second one.
But, like, does this have any game impact?
Not really.
Okay.
Well, that's nice.
Definitely need to make sure that we are making some units.
Yeah.
You see, that's the thing.
You have a limited amount of resources.
Yeah.
And if Montezuma shows up, then you can't spend it all on there.
It's sort of symbolic.
The way that the biggest, the game that DeepMind's DQN stuff has the biggest challenge playing is Montezuma's Revenge.
I haven't thought of that, but that's...
And now Montezuma is screwing with our AI stuff.
Okay, somewhat beautiful.
Damn you, Montezuma.
We will have our revenge.
Slightly excessive force.
I don't like how militarised this whole area has become.
It has become quite militarised.
Oh, you can capture the walker.
Oh, they move closer.
That was clever.
That was really nice of them.
Idiots.
I wonder if the Americans are going to declare war on us.
I hope not.
Oh, these guys.
Can they get their guns on?
Oh, yeah.
They can get their guns on.
In fact, they can kill off those.
That's hilarious.
Yeah.
Because railways are so cheap to move on.
That is true.
But they represent it by running extremely fast.
I guess we need soldiers.
Yeah, you can do bombers.
Yeah, I'm going to screw up Montezuma with bombers.
Oh, has it really?
Oh, wow.
As long as we give him all of our stuff.
That's hilarious.
Absolutely all of our stuff.
That's really an amusing offer.
It is.
I think that's...
Are you tempted?
You know...
Sorry, I'm just looking at his face.
I think he's not making eye contact because...
He looks super distracted.
What?
What's over there?
I think he just looks shifty.
Yeah, I think that's like...
I am bluffing.
I don't know if you know, but I am bluffing.
Bomber?
I like bombers.
Hang on.
Are we already building a bomber in Nottingham?
Yeah, but you can go up to as much oil as you have.
And we've got plenty of oil.
Yeah.
Yeah, I like bombers too.
They're cool.
But I'm really annoyed that we have to do all of this crap,
like military stuff, instead of...
It just feels wasteful, you know?
Maybe.
Just burning a bunch of resources on each other.
I mean, listen.
That's what we do.
I kind of feel a little bit bad about it,
but not really.
Yeah.
Maybe he should sue for peace in a way that isn't just
give us everything you own.
Ha!
Really?
That's mean.
And it's just so unnecessary.
Why?
Okay, that's not good.
What did I do?
Okay.
Oh, that's not good.
What are you talking about, wanton aggression?
What's he talking about?
I don't know.
I think he just wants to do some land grab
and he's making up excuses.
Not that Denmarkans would ever do that in real life.
No, that's not a thing that happens, but...
This is not a thing that happens.
This is, you know...
This is Washington the Terrible.
He's become the terrible.
He has become the terrible.
He was a doge before.
Yeah.
They're all so warmongery.
What in the hell is going on?
I mean, to be fair, when we went around,
everyone was militaristic.
And that should have been a clue.
I don't like this.
Okay, very well.
Okay, but he has a lot of troops around our cities.
Yeah, we're really in trouble.
Yeah.
Yeah, we are.
Let me just...
Is anybody not at war with us?
Us here.
I don't even like them.
I mean, are we screwed at this point?
I mean, we're not going to get to AI research anytime soon,
but no one else is either.
So this can just play out
and then we get back on track.
Yeah, okay.
All right, wartime.
I mean, it is 1943.
You kind of expect there to be a world war going on.
But it's not a world war.
It's everyone at war with us.
That doesn't count as a world war.
Is there a way to know if any of these guys are at war with each other?
I think we would have known.
I think they are not.
London's made a bomber.
Good job, London.
Does that mean we have two bombers in London now?
Yes.
Nice.
Why are their production so slow?
I don't know.
How would we find that out?
Go into the city.
Huh, because they've taken all of their people
and stuck them in the university and in the public school.
Yes, if you take them out of the university and the public school
and back into the mines...
I mean, it's war.
Dig for victory.
There are two sea units here and two ships.
Which probably means we can just get rid of both of them.
Neat.
This is a slightly confusing game to play sometimes.
Yes.
Okay.
Hang on.
There are no more offensive units in the counter-barrier.
Yes.
That was well done.
That's hilarious.
Man, naval superiority is kind of a laugh.
The initial foray of Greek troops just didn't do anything.
Yes.
Luckily for us.
It's embarrassing, to be honest.
Yes.
Please, get wrecked.
I like that it's like a Lancaster bomber.
Oh.
I've got to say, I remember the Second World War going quite differently.
I don't think we were at war with the US.
We were at war with the US.
On the outskirts of Nottingham, not far from Dublin.
Right.
Oh, good.
Nice.
Okay.
All right.
I'm feeling less worried about this one.
Yes.
I mean, we are still at war with literally everyone we've ever met.
Except Songhai.
Except Songhai, for some completely unknown reason.
The by far most warlike looking of all of them.
Maybe except Montezuma.
Yes, with the skulls.
He maybe should realise he's the baddies.
He's literally covered in skulls in front of the wall of skulls.
We're sure that we're on the side of the good here.
Wait, what?
What?
There are those soldiers outside of Nottingham.
And a Greek destroyer found them.
What?
What is the Greeks doing all the way over there?
All right, fine.
Yeah.
Artillery, get him.
Good.
It's always funny when artillery just completely destroys one guy.
I'm sorry, random American soldiers.
It's not going to be your day.
They should not have declared war.
It did seem unnecessary.
But we do now have a stupid amount of air power, so...
Maybe people just got afraid of us?
Hmm.
That guy's scary, let's piss him off.
Okay, go over there and finish it.
You cowards.
And if it'll make you feel better,
a great general is going to help you out.
Oh my God, he gets a little jeep.
Yep.
That's adorable.
And a flag.
He's driving a jeep on the railway tracks.
Yep.
He doesn't care.
He's a great general.
That should teach them a lesson.
Yeah.
Yep.
Please continue getting wrecked.
Phew.
Yeah.
That was a slaughter.
Gentlemen.
Those bombs didn't even explode.
I think they literally just physically hit them with bombs.
It's not even...
It's thinking about it.
Yep.
Nice.
This is still so wasteful, though.
It's completely consumed all of our resources for many turns.
True.
And it is 9.45.
It's time to go around so I can make peace.
Oh yeah.
Do you think they do that deliberately?
No.
Oh, Montezuma wants a peace treaty.
Interesting.
I accept that deal.
That seems reasonable.
Very reasonable.
You're like random...
Yeah.
Back to being friendly.
What in the hell is up with Montezuma?
Are you kidding me?!
What weakness?!
I have, like, seven bombers!
You have a sword!
What are you doing?!
You think we should not have trusted the guy with the burning cities in the background?
Maybe.
Listen, Askia.
If I'm honest, I've never heard of Songhai.
I know this is insulting.
What is...
Where in the world was Songhai?
I feel this...
I mean, I'm revealing weaknesses in my history education.
What is...
Where is...
Do you know?
No.
Well, okay.
We'll deal with this guy.
Very well.
Jolly good show.
More wars.
That's fine.
You know, we don't mind a bit of a war.
And now Florence has declared war on us.
We've discovered computers!
Finally!
A great scientist has been born in the city of Nottingham.
How about that?
What is the name of the scientist in Nottingham?
Where's my scientist?
Show me my scientist.
Where is he?
He's behind the artillery.
There's scientists often are.
Hiding behind the artillery.
There he is.
No, that's the general.
Here we are.
It's Leibniz!
Of course, okay.
We've got Leibniz.
He can rush a technology.
Let's look at the tech tree.
So we got computers.
Now we can rush AI.
That's good.
Discover technology.
And then you have that golden science file.
Ah, okay.
Right, right, right, right.
And I can just...
Oh, wow.
I could get any of these things.
Any of these things.
But I think AI is the most powerful.
Yeah, let's do it.
Alright, we're in it now.
Let's win the game.
The question of whether machines can think is about as relevant as the question of whether submarines can swim.
Okay, it lets us build an AI lab.
Good.
So, maybe we should explain.
That technology, artificial intelligence, is like...
Well, what's the point if you have discovered artificial intelligence?
So it's the field of artificial intelligence.
So it's something like the Turing paper in mind, or the Dartmouth summer school.
It's like, hey, we have computers now.
Maybe we can use them to solve this thing.
Maybe they can think, like a submarine.
Yeah.
So, we've got AI.
If we can also get robotics, then we can get the orthogonality thesis.
Yeah.
Which is necessary if we want to build the AI safety lab.
Because right now we can build the AI lab, but that's just going to cause a bad outcome without any safety research.
Having discovered artificial intelligence, your researchers may now start working towards superintelligence.
Manage your research through the artificial intelligence screen.
You guys made a whole screen.
Yeah.
Wow.
You can click the thing.
And it will bring up the screen.
Yeah.
Okay.
So our AI research level is zero, because we haven't even finished our first AI lab.
From local research, also zero.
From open research by others, also zero.
And I don't know who's going to help us, because America's at war with us.
The only people not at war with us are the Aztecs.
Yeah, but even people who are at war with you, if they publish, you can pick up the research.
So a treaty on AI would share all research and guarantee that values of both civilizations are built into the AI being developed.
I haven't signed any treaties.
Yeah, because everyone but Guantanamo is at war with me.
I think you said in the interview, one thing you've discovered is that if everyone's at war, AI cooperation becomes difficult.
Yeah.
Maybe we should just point out that you can get to that screen both from that AI counter that has now appeared on your top.
Oh, yeah.
So you can kind of quickly see that.
And it's also, if you look at the kind of menus, so the little scroll icon.
Yeah.
And then AI is at the top.
Ah.
Cool.
Okay.
If you click on that thing before, then it just says AI has not been developed yet.
So it's time to build some AI labs and some AI safety labs.
Well, I mean, it's time to maybe not be at war with literally everyone.
I don't know, man.
You've done nothing to us of consequence.
The worst thing you did was when that destroyer destroyed my infantry that was annoying Montezuma.
Nothing else you've done.
Do you remember when I steamrolled three of your units on the ocean?
Never mind.
Even his horse looks angry.
It's not the time for negotiation.
All right.
I guess we're going to have to kick some ass.
You will never get horses.
It's never going to happen.
You're so mean.
Well, I sued for peace, man.
He didn't want it.
That is true.
So London is not making that.
London's going to make an AI lab.
Do you think it's realistic for there to be an AI lab in London?
Well, I mean, for realism, Nottingham should have the first one.
But then after that, I think there could be one in London.
This is an idiot.
But okay.
I mean, I admire your guts.
Strewn all over the jungle.
Oh, wow.
What?
He's really tired of war.
I'm inclined to accept.
I see no reason not to.
I've always wanted horses.
Now we have all of them.
Like Alexander.
He's bound to lose now.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
For sure.
He's a Doge again.
Yeah.
And technically, I'm still at war with Greece.
He's just rubbish at it.
Yeah.
Why do people keep declaring war on me when it works out terribly for them every time?
Because you're afraid you'll win?
Well, I should just deal with it.
Uh.
Another bubble.
What does our economic advisor say?
A windmill, really?
We could build Green's Windmill.
It's in Nottingham.
There's a windmill.
And it's the science windmill.
It's going to give us extra science.
I mean, it will speed up building science buildings.
So you got that.
Good.
We're building Green's Windmill.
Okay.
You seem to be very pleased with that.
I am.
I used to live right near it.
It's cool.
It's like a little science museum.
Oh, I want these guys to build oil.
So that we can have more battleships.
No, wait.
We're technically still at war with Greece.
I feel like Alexander would be deeply offended that I keep forgetting we're at war with him.
Just like, oh, yeah.
We are at war with you.
It's just like you're not doing anything threatening.
Nottingham.
Build the windmill.
It built the windmill.
Yes.
We have Green's Windmill.
Good.
Now all of our science is going to be extra sciencey.
Yes.
Huh.
Sure, you big idiot.
Okay.
The world is finally becoming slightly less belligerent.
Yeah.
Keep bombing the sh** out of people until they stop being so damn belligerent.
Okay.
It's...
It's Louis Daguerre.
It is.
Inventor of the...
Of photography?
Wasn't he?
Well, clearly he should be rushing Deep Blue when the time comes.
Louis Daguerre.
French artist and photographer.
Recognized for his invention of the Daguerreotype process of photography.
Neat.
Okay.
Father of photography.
He's in Nottingham.
Does it matter where Deep Blue is built?
No.
Well then, Deep Blue is built in Nottingham.
Yeah.
We're rewriting history.
Sleeping there until you discover...
Data mining.
Okay.
Alright, we're researching the orthogonality thesis.
You know, we put all of this extra information in the civilopedia,
so if you don't know what the orthogonality thesis is,
you can actually find out about it.
That's a good point.
If anybody didn't...
Oh, what?
The geeks.
They came up.
Damn it.
Yeah, so if you didn't watch my most recent video about the orthogonality thesis,
you could watch that.
Or we can look in the...
Help.
There you go, the text.
Tech stuff.
Yeah.
Modern era.
Here we are.
So this is a technology, an area of research that lets you build the AI safety lab.
To reduce the chances of rogue superintelligence eliminating the human race.
And it even has this...
That's pretty great.
The statement of the orthogonality thesis on the bottom.
Right.
Intelligence and final goals are orthogonal axes along which possible agents can freely vary.
In other words, more or less any level of intelligence could in principle be combined with more or less any final goal.
Okay.
How's that for a hidden message in a mod?
It's very subtle.
Yeah, if you think this is important, I mean, check out this guy's channel.
I mean, they're watching a video on my channel, so...
That is true.
So we also have descriptions for artificial intelligence.
Yeah.
This is really nicely done.
Compliments to Shai Shapira, actually.
Yeah, he deserves credit.
So you need data mining to build Deep Blue.
So that's good.
Let's get some of that.
How are we doing on our tech tree?
We've just started on the orthogonality thesis.
Yeah.
So does that mean I need de-globalization?
Oh no.
So you need to go all the way back to that.
So I actually need ecology?
Yeah.
Well, before that, you need penicillin and plastics.
Oh no!
Yeah, so all of that.
Ah.
I thought I was so close to, like, cracking the code.
Not quite there yet.
But it turns out...
But you see?
So, in fact, after AI, if you want, you can just drop orthogonality thesis and go down the other route to get capability research.
If you just trust someone else to do safety for you.
So you went from AI down to robotics to orthogonality thesis.
But after AI, you could have just gone back to penicillin, plastics, ecology, globalization, data mining.
So you could do just AI capabilities with never bothering with safety.
Right.
Because you just trust that other people will handle it for you.
Yep.
Hmm.
I don't trust anyone else because literally everyone...
Literally every other civ has at some time or another declared war on me for no reason.
Yeah, this is not a particularly altruistic world.
Yeah.
So I feel as though if I'm going to do AI right, I've got to do it myself.
It's going to be a made-in-Britain AI.
Oh!
Oh, statistics!
Maybe they'll be friends with us.
Maybe.
Maybe they'll declare war on us for no goddamn reason.
I want to build...
In fact, I'm going to do it just because I like the idea of the Statue of Liberty being in York.
So I'm actually at peace with these guys.
Yeah.
That's novel.
No, I'm actually at peace now with more people than I'm at war with.
Yep.
So I feel good about that.
Where is Russia anyway?
I don't know.
We haven't found them.
We...
Freaking...
Possibly upstairs somewhere.
Stealth Russia.
Maybe it's over here.
Nobody knows for sure.
Okay.
That means I'm really big.
What is Russia?
We just don't know.
Okay, so Hastings needs to decide what to do.
Yeah.
I think they should have an AI lab as well.
Of course.
Everyone should have an AI lab.
Yeah.
One for you and one for you.
Everybody gets an AI lab.
No, I'll keep him guarding because the Russians could come from anywhere because we don't know where they are.
Phil.
So just head off that way.
Oh, okay.
I think we found the Russians.
Ah, there it is.
There's the border.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, that's good to know.
That's one way to find.
Oh.
What?
You will not be able to build...
Whoa.
Ah, they were coordinating with each other.
Russia and the Greeks decided to do their big attack all at once.
Huh.
That's cute.
I'm really tempted to just take these horse people, though.
Sure.
Because I could do it in one turn with these infantry.
You know what?
I'm going to because that's going to really, really annoy him.
I know he's fictional, but...
We're 10% of the way towards AGI.
So...
How's the risk going?
So we're doing 84 of it.
We're doing actually all of the AI research, aren't we?
No, it's just that of our research, it's all in-house.
We're not getting from anyone else.
Gotcha.
Because everyone's at war with us.
The danger of rogue superintelligence is 98, though.
Yeah.
So somebody else out there is doing AI research.
Yes.
And it's weird that we know that.
Because we don't know that, right?
Yeah, that's true.
But you kind of...
It's really bad springing bad conditions on players without letting them know it's happening.
Yeah.
So, I mean...
In reality, we have no idea how close we are to superintelligence.
Or to superintelligence risk.
Having a clear number that you're aiming at is nothing like reality.
But it makes a lot of sense from a game mechanic design.
Yeah.
So in general, in the mod, you kind of have to go either realistic, this is important to us to capture height.
Or if we do it this way, it's not going to be fun to play.
Right.
Yeah, that's the same thing, I think.
People, they ask like, okay, so when is it going to happen?
How long is it going to take?
Where are we?
Right?
Everybody wants to believe that we actually know how far away we are.
It's unknown unknowns, right?
Yeah.
If we knew exactly what the problems were that we needed to solve, and how long it would take to solve them,
we would already be most of the way to solving them.
That is true.
I mean, look at the record of humanity.
We're not very good at forecasting technology progress.
That's true.
Particularly for things that are brand new.
Yeah.
Look at development of nuclear weapons.
You had some people kind of actively working on it.
Other people saying it's never going to happen.
Yeah.
Applications of electricity.
I mean, go back as far as you want to really transformative technologies.
It's kind of, if you have a rough idea of how it's going to work, then you have some timeline in your head.
But a lot of it depends on things that you don't know until you're going to try them.
And if you don't have a timeline in your head, then you just have some vague arguments about why it's never going to happen.
Yeah.
That's often the distribution of predictions that you have.
But here, in the land of fiction and games, we know that we're 10% of the way there.
Yeah.
But...
But the risk is outpacing our own progress.
Right.
Which would make sense if a lot of people are working on it.
So to clarify the rules here, if this hits 800 before this hits 800...
Everyone dies.
We're screwed.
Okay.
If we're trying to get AI...
Right.
And specifically AI safety, what are the things we're going to need?
So you're going to need AI safety labs.
Right.
Which you can build once you discover Oroginality's thesis.
Okay.
Which I think is not very far in the future.
So what I'm going to want once I actually have AI labs, once I have AI safety labs, is research capability.
Right?
So is there anything I can build now that will increase my research capability?
So in terms of research, you've maxed out on currently available tech.
You have the university and the public school.
Yep.
And you haven't discovered the thing that lets you build research labs yet.
Right.
But you will also want to have lots of populations, so you can have excess population to put as AI specialists.
So I want happiness.
So that's both happiness and food.
Right.
So aqueduct and stadium are both relevant to that?
Yeah.
And you would want to have money, so you could put it into treaties and the safety fund.
Gotcha.
Alright, well I'll go with the aqueduct then because it's super quick.
Sure.
Nice.
Hey!
We've researched the orthogonality thesis!
The greatest task before civilization at present is to make machines what they ought to be.
The slaves instead of the masters of men.
Wow, when was that written?
I should go and look it up.
Also, I'm not sure we want slaves, but we definitely don't want them to be masters either.
Yeah, I was thinking that.
Like, slaves feels very anthropomorphic.
I envision well-aligned AGI as just wanting the things that we want so that we don't need to enslave it or control it.
It's free to do what it wants, and what it wants to do is good things.
Yeah.
I kind of really like the minds in the culture novels.
Oh yeah?
If we get it right, this is what it might look like.
We have this kind of other that wants what we want.
So these are novels by...
Ian M. Banks.
Right, Ian M. Banks.
They're officially recommended novels, there you go.
Yeah, yeah, I agree though.
The culture seems to have a good...
It's not perfect, but it's sort of a plausible good outcome.
Yes.
I mean, as with anything.
This is beyond the pale of transformative technology.
We don't know what the outcome is going to look like.
But it's nice to have some positive visions that don't involve slaves or masters.
Right.
I agree.
So, we can build AI safety labs.
This is exciting times.
We're now at 102 AI and 118.
Which probably means it's not an AI lab in a city-state.
It's just minor accidents.
So we have made it so that whenever there is AI research...
Right.
You occasionally get some chance of extra risk being generated by any of the labs.
Oh, okay.
It's kind of...
Someone forgot to run the set of tests before committing the code.
What would be an example of the kind of thing you're thinking of?
So, say there is a software bug in a common AI framework.
Okay.
Right?
Yep.
It goes in there.
It goes undetected.
Many years down the line, either a human adversary decides to exploit that vulnerability...
Mm-hmm.
Or a system that's under an optimization pressure finds a way of exploiting that vulnerability.
So it's just a little bit more risk built into your system.
Because you haven't designed anything in advance to be as safe and secure as possible.
Right.
So things like terminating strings with nulls at the end, other than having the length at the beginning...
Opens up a whole category of buffer overflows.
Right.
It in itself doesn't cause any harm.
But it just increases the risk of something bad happening further down the line.
So in the real world, then, we probably have a huge amount of that.
Because most people writing most software, including AI software, are not making an extraordinary effort to make sure that their code is very secure and robust.
Yes.
There is a paper whose name of which I'm not currently remembering.
I think it had demons in it.
This one.
I'm just making editing work for myself now.
I'm not going to do that.
Okay.
Yeah.
But they survey security vulnerabilities in common AI frameworks.
And they find a whole bunch of them.
Interesting.
Okay.
That's cool.
I will link to that paper if I remember to.
I guess just more bombardment.
That's fine.
And I'm going to use it to screw over these horses.
Because that's my number one priority.
Surely the people trying to capture the horses.
Right.
No, I love horses.
I love horses.
As a true Englishman, I'm a friend to all animals.
In the AI screen, you can get to either by clicking on the AI progress bar or phone bell.
You can now access the AI safety fund.
Ah.
So there are no AI safety labs in the world.
True.
I can invest in a city state to establish an AI safety lab.
Do I have the money?
I do not have the money.
You don't have the money.
These are quite expensive.
Yeah, okay.
Huh.
There's no point in this conflict continuing any further.
Except he wants quite a bit of your money.
He wants all of my money.
Okay, how about we just, you know...
No?
No.
Alright, I mean, I've got a lot of bombers that I don't feel like selling and not enough Russians to attack, so I'm fine with that.
York has finished its safety lab.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay, let's go into the city.
Yeah.
Okay.
So you see how all of these specialist buildings...
Yep.
...have spots next to them?
Mm-hmm.
So you can manually assign people to work in them.
Ah, so right now we have a guy in the factory and that's it.
An engineer in the factory, yeah, and nothing else.
Everyone else is out in the fields producing stuff.
Gotcha.
Now, both the AI lab and the AI safety lab have three specialist slots that are currently empty.
So right now we are still ahead on rogue points.
Yeah.
So I want to do more safety and less regular research.
Right.
So I'm going to... Does the fact that this is an engineer, is that more powerful than just putting a dude in there?
Like he's orange instead of green or whatever?
So green people walk the tiles in the land.
Mm-hmm.
So that person, for example, is generating five food and two gold.
Right. He's a fisherman.
Yes.
And he's a fisherman in a place that actually has fish, unlike this guy who's a fisherman in a place that doesn't have any fish.
Dude, stop being a fisherman.
Instead, come with me and be a fisher of AI.
Now he's unemployed.
Yeah. You can just click the... You don't need to do it again. You just click the thing. Yeah.
Ah, nice.
Cool.
Yeah.
Interesting.
A bunch of silver and gold.
I'm okay with that.
I guess she's completely fed up with being at war, right?
Yeah. Also, she has no more units on our borders to bomb.
Yeah. Yeah, we really did just destroy everything.
If you had any units, I would say let's make war with Greece.
You know, to just finish them off, too.
But that's fine. I accept.
Yeah. You're welcome, you idiot.
Oh, actually, I should talk to Greece before we get into this.
Hmm.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I think it is. Yeah.
A peace treaty.
Hey!
Do we want anything else from them?
A research pact?
They don't have the money.
Yeah, because you've been spending it all on units that I immediately destroy.
No, he doesn't want it.
What do you want? What do you want to end it?
Yes.
Alright.
I'm going to bomb the hell out of Sparta, then.
I mean, I don't see that you've really left me much choice.
It's funny, the prerequisites for the orthogonality thesis,
because you would think it would be,
all you need is to just think about it a little bit.
Hmm.
Did we just destroy their jets?
Yeah, we did.
Nice.
So, nowadays, thinking about the orthogonality thesis is a bit hard
without having thought about AI as a thing yet.
Hmm.
And also having AI as a thing, but not having thought about robotics very much.
I guess instrumental goals are more salient
when you have these systems that are actually meant to be in environments
and doing various things.
Sure. Yeah, that makes sense.
I guess it's kind of interesting, like,
it's very hard to know which ideas are obvious,
because there are so many things that seem obvious in retrospect.
You know?
I shouldn't be bombing this guy.
I should be taking these horse people are the absolute priority.
What am I doing?
You can just do that.
Yeah.
So, imagine, like, early days of AI.
The idea was that you were just going to hard-code everything.
With such a system, safety concerns are not obvious.
Sure, the system only does what you tell it to do.
And that is still kind of received wisdom about AI.
Yeah.
But once you start thinking with robotics,
you realize that something like reinforcement learning
is going to be a lot more salient.
Now, machine learning is only going to come up much later in the tech tree.
But I think the earliest is when you start mixing the idea
of having computers think for themselves
and realizing that this is going to be much harder
than just coding everything by hand.
Right.
That actually there's a level of unpredictability there.
Yeah.
Which people didn't realize early on.
I think the maximum of how things are easy and easy things are hard
came from people who were very much working on robotics.
Right.
Yeah, that's really true.
The things that seem easy to human beings
are the things that we've been doing for so long
that we're kind of running in specialized hardware.
Yeah.
They're easy because we don't have to think about it
because they're things that we're highly optimized to do.
Yeah.
And that includes some of our morality.
Right?
We just know that something will make us super embarrassed
or just feel really guilty.
Right, yeah.
I guess that is like low-level support for morality.
It's instinctive.
Yeah.
And so it feels super obvious.
But it's not going to be easy, obvious to code this into an AI.
This thing that was put in place by a tremendously long process of evolution
doing game theory
with all of these specialized ad hoc twists and turns and details.
Funny that we're sitting here chatting about morality
as you're bombing the outskirts of Sparta.
They're not people, though.
You're correct.
They're simulations of people.
And they have been mean to you.
They've been mean to me.
And they refuse to make peace.
Yes.
And they are like...
Not only are they simulations of people,
but they're like...
They're not accurate simulations of people either, you know?
True.
They're not high detail enough to have moral weight.
I just want to look at him again.
Hi.
He's calling you his friend.
Yeah.
That's his friend's face.
So...
So you're going to cities on his side?
Oh, right.
Yeah, cities.
And then pick Dublin.
Dublin.
What do you want for Dublin?
No, you don't.
No, you're really, really into Dublin.
Yeah.
Okay, the Aztecs, way into Dublin.
That's fair.
Dublin's nice.
I mean, it's a nice place.
It is a nice place.
Okay, um...
Best Guinness I've ever tasted.
Yeah, yeah, because it's fresh.
Yeah, it actually tastes different, though.
Yeah.
Ah.
Pfft.
I mean, I could.
Are there any horses?
No.
I'll leave them.
So kind.
I don't like killing civilians for no reason.
So...
Um...
I feel civilians don't like being killed for no reason.
Get out of the temple.
What are you doing?
Get in the lab.
So what did we have?
Two in the factory, two in the university.
That seems sensible.
Yeah.
And you had one in the windmill.
Is that Green's windmill?
How are we doing with the numbers?
Yeah, yeah, that's Green's windmill.
We need somebody in there.
Oh, you've caught up.
Yes.
We may actually win this.
Yeah.
I feel good about it.
It does seem like no one else is in the race,
which makes it a lot easier to win.
Yeah.
I feel terrible.
It's not...
The thing is, it's not Sparta's fault
that Alexander is an idiot.
I'm just going to sue for peace one more time.
Fair.
He keeps saying that.
But he's not standing behind his...
Ah!
Finally!
Thank you.
How long have we been at war with Greece?
I think since...
Since the 40s?
It's been 30 years.
It's a 30-year war.
Make peace.
Yeah.
You can do this with all the city-states now.
I'm at war with Florence,
who I'm pretty sure I've never seen,
but fine.
Yeah.
Let's make peace.
Yeah, cool.
Thanks, man.
And Kathmandu.
Yeah.
Hey!
And Stockholm.
Wait, what?
Oh, they're at war as well.
Ha!
Yeah.
Did I just make world peace?
I think I just made world peace.
It was surprisingly easy.
I don't really understand the AI safety fund mechanic.
So it's just getting another safety lab.
Right.
So say you're going for a challenge
and you only have one city.
That means you can only have one safety lab,
which means at most you have
about six safety per turn.
I see.
Which is clearly not enough
to balance the world's needs,
but you can use this fund
to establish safety labs all over the world.
I see.
So if you're low on cities
but cash-rich,
you can establish safety labs somewhere else.
Yeah.
And we've finished researching...
Ecology.
So we can get globalization.
Yeah.
That's good.
And then that lets us get data mining.
Okay.
Which almost makes sense.
Oh, and now that you've built universities
in all your cities,
you can build Oxford University.
Interesting.
If we had more budget,
I would have just changed its name to Cambridge.
But...
Gazitvlax is like Oxford,
and, I mean, I'm a fan as well.
Not quite as good as Cambridge,
but not that bad either.
Yeah, yeah.
I...
I'm not going to say bad things about Oxford.
But, um...
I prefer Cambridge too.
Uh, but I...
In the absence of Cambridge,
I think it's a good idea to build this.
Because it gives plus three science...
And a free technology.
And we really could use both of those.
My AI researchers have reached
the level of advanced AI.
The new AI manufacturing technique
will give you a 20% increase
to production in all cities.
Well, that's great.
I'm really on track to win this one then.
Yep.
Thank you all.
How's Blisk?
Yeah, our AI research level
is higher than our rogue.
Yeah, and no one seems to be
going off the air.
What are satellites?
Reveal the entire map.
That sounds great.
Okay, so you can...
I'll get rocketry.
Okay.
Cool.
A good rule for rocket experimenters
to follow is this.
Always assume that it will explode.
That also applies to AI.
It really does.
Yeah.
Oh, you could build the Apollo program.
Well, yeah.
You can't.
Because we removed all of that
from the game.
Okay.
But that gets you a science victory.
Yeah.
So, basically,
we took the original science victory
from the game,
which is you build the Apollo program,
you build a spaceship,
you launch it to Alpha Centauri,
and instead we said,
you win a science victory
if you build an
aligned superintelligence.
Oh, so you would notice
that you can now build
a smart defense grid?
Improves the defense of the city.
Must have advanced AI to build.
Increases risk of rogue superintelligence
by one per turn.
Ah.
So if we were still at war
and we started trying to use
our AI stuff in a military way,
that would give us a big advantage,
but also increase risk.
Yeah.
So usually the defense buildings,
you kind of need to build them
one after the other.
So you build walls,
and then you build the thing
that comes after walls.
I think it's a military base
or something like that.
They kind of stack up,
but walls give you
plus four defense.
Right.
Smart defense grid says,
forget all of that.
You can just automate your defenses.
You get plus 15 to your defense,
which is quite a lot.
Right.
But A, you can't build it
until you've reached this threshold,
and B, it does come with some risk.
Right.
Because you've got a whole bunch
of military type stuff
being software controlled,
and you're also researching
more military type stuff.
Yep.
That makes sense.
Oh, he has wine.
Hey, and he has excess wine.
Yeah.
Maybe he wants cotton for it.
Yeah, you want some,
you want some,
where's my cotton?
You want some cotton?
Yay!
Good.
Well done.
And everybody's happy
because we have wine.
Again, once more,
Britain has wine.
How about this year?
And there was much rejoicing.
That's a lot of Aztec troops.
Where are they?
I mean,
they're not technologically advanced.
I'm curious about
what the Aztecs are up to.
Where am I?
They're invading Greece.
They're in Greece's land.
Maybe they have
open borders with them though.
Ah.
We have data mining.
That allows us to build Deep Blue.
That sounds good.
Yeah.
I guess we're just being okay
with Canterbury being
surrounded by Aztecs.
I mean, we have a lot of bombers.
Hastings has finished
their research lab.
Yeah.
Oh, I could build
a military AI lab.
Yeah.
That gives you 30 experience
for all units.
You must have advanced AI
to build it.
It increases risk
of rogue super intelligence
by two per turn.
Yeah.
So this is even worse
than a smart defense grid
because now we're talking
about offensive capabilities.
Yeah.
So this is the same.
There is the kind of barracks
that leads to the armory
that leads to the military academy
that gives you
extra experience.
So you know how
all of the units we created
got one improved,
one upgrade
as we created them?
Yep.
It's because we started
in the modern age.
So you have a barracks
in all of your cities?
Right.
Plus 30 means that you will get
two upgrades
just as you create them.
Yeah.
So this is like,
I feel like there's all kinds
of game mechanics here
that we're just not using
by virtue of being too good.
Yeah.
We've played too well
and there are problems
that we're just not even facing
like how to balance
the necessary military benefit
that we need to survive.
With AI risk.
Versus world AI risk.
Hmm.
I'm very uncomfortable
about this.
Hey!
The game of chess
is not merely an idle amusement.
Several very valuable qualities
of the mind
useful in the course
of life are to be acquired
and strengthened by it
so as to become habits
ready on all occasions.
For life is a kind of chess.
Thanks, Benjamin Franklin.
Hmm.
He's on my underwear.
Actually, I'm wearing
Benjamin Franklin underwear.
It's true.
That's good to know.
Yeah.
It's a hundred dollar bill
underwear, but...
Hmm.
Okay.
So this now means that
artists provide
plus one AI research.
I don't have any artists.
Do I?
No.
You have other people
you put in temples
and museums.
Ah.
I took somebody out of the temple
actually, didn't I?
Okay.
Now we can build a data center.
Yep.
It's the future.
It became the future.
Yep.
Jonathan Colton was right.
Okay.
So...
So the idea with Deep Blue
is that it captures
society's mind
so it's not just
AI researchers
that are now able
to contribute
to this technological progress.
Ah.
Lots of other people
suddenly become
part of it.
Right.
It becomes
more of an
interdisciplinary
thing.
Yes.
Almost a social movement,
if you like.
And in the midst of all of this
all hell apparently
is breaking loose.
Does it involve us?
I feel like it's gonna.
Huh.
You were right.
Hey, he has changed
his facial expression.
Yeah, he looks a lot...
He looks about the same angry.
It's just a bit different.
He looks like a different
kind of angry now.
He looks a bit...
I don't know.
He looks like he just
spilled his pint.
Yeah.
That's exactly what he looks like.
Very well,
you big moron.
And there is an
unprotected general
outside London
that the tank
can just steam all over.
He never was very bright,
was he, Montezuma?
I spent all this time
building missile cruisers
and tanks and things
and didn't get to use them
and now I get to use them.
Bombers,
awaken.
I feel bad
for the Aztecs, man.
I feel embarrassed
on their behalf.
Agbar was
Bonnie Nottingham.
Cool.
I'm gonna assume
that he's the
Star Wars guy,
the fish one.
Mm-hmm.
I'm gonna assume
that he's the
Star Wars guy,
the fish one.
Combat with bombers
is, like,
very effective
but not actually that fun.
Oh.
Okay.
Piss off, Montezuma.
I don't-
I don't understand
Montezuma at all.
How much is this war
gonna have to cost him
before he realises
it's stupid?
Cool.
Aztecs are just
moving around
but not sending any jets.
I guess they don't
have vision.
Yeah.
And they're not gonna
get vision either
because I'm gonna
blow the crap out of
everything before
it gets close.
Yeah.
I'm annoyed.
I'm annoyed because
I'm trying to do
a nice thing here.
I'm spending a lot
of resources
on AI safety research.
I'm trying to
create utopia
and this guy
who still has
a skull for a hat
is coming at me
with-
I think it's just
feathers on his hat.
World War II.
He's got a golden
skull on it, man.
Look.
Yes.
That is very much
a golden skull.
Right?
Yeah.
What would it take-
No.
Okay.
Just very, very determined
to be stupid
and hurt himself.
So I feel like
AI safety wise
this has been
relatively uneventful.
Yeah.
Because
No one else
has gone for it yet.
Nobody else is going
for that
going for that
win condition.
How are we doing?
We're still
more than double.
Yeah.
So we actually
can be quite safe
to just
max out our AI labs.
Yeah, I guess
in this scenario
it turns out
that alignment
is not so hard.
I guess
OpenAI were wrong
all the time
and Miri were-
Yeah, I mean
I guess
if you have-
Well, if you have
full control
of the project.
Yeah.
There's only one person
and you haven't really
kind of started racing
until you've discovered
what the nullity thesis is
and you've put a bunch of people
on the problem
to begin with.
Yeah.
They could just come up
with a sensible solution.
That would be nice,
wouldn't it?
It'd be lovely.
Yeah.
I don't think
it's the world we're in.
But
counterfactually
there are worlds like that.
I've got atomic theory.
Yeah.
Cool.
Don't need it.
Your AI researchers
have reached the level
of expert AI.
The new AI-driven abundance
increases happiness
in each city by two.
Great.
That's good.
Wow, we're doing really well
and it's just strange
that we're at war
with a crazy-
What is that?
Oh, it's uranium.
Yeah.
It just became uranium.
We never cared about it before
so we didn't notice
that the ground was glowing.
That's exactly right.
Okay.
You know,
you only see things
once you know
that they are there.
Yeah, yeah, that's true.
I do feel bad
attacking Dublin, though.
You're liberating it.
Oh, right,
liberating Dublin, yeah.
We're going to liberate
this s**t out of Dublin.
Bam!
Sorry, Dublin.
You'll thank us
in the future
when you're no longer
a puppet
of ridiculous
golden skull hat man.
I feel bad, though.
I don't-
So sad.
It's such a sadness.
Your move, Montezuma.
It's just been nuked.
It must be so pissed.
Yeah.
Ah!
Fine.
I'm going to
go and get
some water.
I'm going to get
Fine.
Idiot.
I can't get over
how dumb he is.
Your AI research
is one that the risk
of rogue superintelligence
is becoming higher.
Consider dedicating
more resources
to AI safety
to prevent catastrophe.
But that's
because we got 250.
Okay,
we're still about W.
I'm comfortable
with that.
602 now.
We are steadily advancing.
We are extremely happy.
Wow.
Nuclear fission,
fine.
I'm more about fusion
personally.
It is fusion.
Oh, it is fusion.
Yay!
I read fission.
Yeah, you have.
You've had fission
for like
two years now.
Okay.
Good.
You're discovering these things
one a year now.
That's pretty crazy.
We're a heavily
research-oriented civilization.
That is true.
This is Britain.
We care about two things.
AI research
and bombers.
And those horse guys.
So you're making
so much AI research now.
It might just be
Oh my goodness.
Have a look.
Yeah, do it.
What's happening
on AI reform?
Yeah, no one else
has even gone down the path.
Nobody else even cares at all.
Okay.
Fine.
Ah, well,
so it turns out
that's how you avoid
an AI race.
Yes,
you have no one
pursuing it
other than you.
Yeah.
Perfect.
Just make sure
everyone's incredibly militaristic.
I can start
researching future tech.
Yeah.
You're done.
Research tree.
Not much left
for the AI to do for you.
Yeah.
Yeah, I guess
you just became
a tech
speed down
the tech tree.
Use that
to gain
further advantage
of going down
the tech tree.
Yeah.
Everyone else
decided to go militaristic
and it backfired
because we had superiority.
Yeah.
So,
good.
Wouldn't be so easy.
Oh.
Because it passed 500,
is that?
Yeah.
But we're nearly there.
We are nearly there.
Isn't it weird
that
putting people
in the opera house
is better for AI research
than putting them
in the university?
I mean,
have you seen the kind of research
that gets done in universities?
No comment.
Oh,
coming in with tanks now.
Yeah.
Easy peasy.
Anyway,
no concern of ours.
No,
we're just,
like,
double-checking our code.
Yeah!
Well done.
You have achieved victory
through mastery of science.
You have conquered
the mysteries of nature
and ushered in a technology
that makes utopia
within reach.
Your triumph
will be remembered
as long as the stars
burn in the night sky.
Hurrah!
Everything is wonderful
and the sun never sets
on an artificial intelligence-powered
British Empire.
Everything
is wonderful.
is beautiful.
Nothing hurts
and all's for the best
in this best-of-all-possible world.
This video took a lot more
editing work
than my usual videos,
in part because it's
a lot longer
and also because I started
with about nine hours
of gameplay footage.
I had to get some new equipment
to make it all work,
so I want to thank
my excellent
Patreon supporters,
all of these people here,
for making it possible.
In this video,
I'm especially thanking Steve.
Thank you, Steve.
I hope you enjoy the little
behind-the-scenes video
I made about
how this one was put together,
and I've also uploaded
the full, like,
eight-hour-long version
if you want to watch that.
Anyway, thank you again,
and I'll see you next time.
You think you can
make an Instinct video?
I don't know, man.
I'm, like, bloody blind.