Say you've got a huge diamond you want to protect.
So you put it in a cool sci-fi vault
with all sorts of sensors and actuators.
You have an AI system to run the vault,
and the plans it comes up with
might be too complex for you to understand,
but it also predicts the final view from the camera
after the plan happens.
So before you okay a plan,
you can check that the diamond is still there at the end.
But imagine a plan that allows a thief to come in
and set up a screen in front of the camera
showing a diamond.
The predicted outcome looks good,
so you okay the plan and the diamond is stolen.
But this should be avoidable, right?
In order to predict the right fake image,
the AI has to know that the diamond's been stolen.
But how do you get that information out?
Solving this problem in its hardest form
is extremely difficult.
So difficult, in fact,
that the Alignment Research Center
is offering prizes of five to $50,000 for good ideas.
So if you think you've got a solution
based on the description I've just given, you don't.
Read the full technical report.
It's 105 pages of reasons why your idea won't work.
But if you've carefully gone through all of that
and still think you've got something,
send it in, link below.
The deadline is February 15th.
I think I'll have a go myself.