Hi, welcome back. Sorry for the delay in uploading, instead of our regularly scheduled video,
today we're going to have a quick comparison between this, my laptop, and this, a paper
A4 notebook. Which one's lighter? They feel about the same. Call that a draw. Which one's
thinner? About the same. Which one's better at editing videos that are more than a few
minutes long? Hang on, let me check. Yeah, neither of them can do that. At all. I had
the first video all shot and worked out, and I've been trying to edit it for a long time
now, but it's just not going to work. The laptop is not powerful enough. So, long story
short, I'm building a PC. Parts are on the way. I'm going to delete this video obviously
when I get the actual one up, but just have patience, and I'll see you again soon.
Quiet on set!