Hi, my name's Rob Miles, welcome to my channel.
It seems pretty likely that sooner or later we'll develop general artificial intelligence.
That is to say, a software system that's able to reason about the world in general and take
actions in the world at large.
We don't know how to do that yet, but before we figure it out, it would be good to know
for sure that any such system we create would be safe, would be positive, would be beneficial
to humanity.
It's not as easy as it sounds.
On this channel, we'll talk about machine learning and artificial intelligence.
We'll look at some of the problems of AI safety and some of the work being done right now
on those problems.
If that kind of thing sounds interesting to you, hit the subscribe button.
You may also want to hit the little bell if you want to be notified when new videos come
out.
And more importantly, if you know anyone who you think might be interested in this kind
of thing, send them a link.
Yeah, that's it for now.
New videos coming soon.
Watch this space.
Ah.
Perfect.
Yeah.
That's the take.
Use that one.