So, Go is a very, very simple game in terms of the rules, but it's very difficult computationally.
There's an enormous depth of complexity that comes out of the very simple rules,
which is, I think, part of what makes people love it so much as a game.
So, to understand why it's hard for computers, I guess you have to go back a whole bunch
and talk about just how computers play games in general, these sort of turn-based strategy games,
or that kind of thing, and start with something easy, like Noughts & Crosses.
For the sake of internationalization, yes, tic-tac-toe.
I like Noughts & Crosses as a name, because it's descriptive, you know, but whatever, yeah.
We're going to look at Noughts & Crosses as a game, and I'm going to keep calling it that, I apologise, but...
You don't have to apologise, I just want to make sure people understand what we're talking about.
Right, right, right, right.
That's all.
So I'm talking about this game, where you draw your Optothorpe, and then one person, you know, goes here,
and one person goes there, and so on, and you alternate placing Noughts and Crosses, and you have to get three in a row.
To explain Noughts & Crosses, we should play an even simpler game.
So the idea of the game is, we're going to take it in turns to choose left or right,
and I'm going to try and get the highest number possible, and you're going to try and get the lowest number possible.
It starts off my turn, so if I choose left, for example, it goes down to here.
And then it's your turn, and you get to choose left or right.
And then which number it ends up on is the outcome of the game.
So I want the highest number possible, which is 7.
You want the lowest number possible, which is 1.
Failing that, I'd prefer the 5 to the 3.
This is a perfect information game.
What's the difference? What's an imperfect information game?
Right, right. So a perfect information game is just a game where all of the players have all of the relevant information.
So this is like that, Noughts & Crosses is like that, chess, Go, these sorts of games.
You do get games that are not like that.
For example, poker.
There's hidden information. You can't see each other's hands.
So you have to, if you want to write something that's going to play those types of games,
obviously it has to work differently to take into account that uncertainty.
The question is, should I choose left or right, and how do I make a principled decision?
Now, I want the 7.
So in principle, I should be going this way, right?
You would think I'd want to steer towards the 7.
But on the other hand, at this point, it's your choice.
You're not going to choose the 7, because I know you want the low number.
You're going to choose the 1.
If I'm choosing this node, I'm effectively choosing the 1, because I can predict you'll do that.
Whereas if I choose the right, then your choice is between a 3 and a 5.
So you are going to choose the 3, which is better than the 1, so I should go right.
I'm trying to maximize the minimum value.
I'm trying to make it so that the best choice available to you is as bad as possible for you,
and as good as possible for me.
So this is called minimax, because I'm trying to minimize the max.
Well, you're trying to minimize the maximum, I'm trying to maximize the minimum.
If you see what I mean.
And then purely based upon who goes first as to who wins this, right?
Right, yeah. This is an absolutely unfair game.
I started off saying I want the 7, so maybe I should go left to get the 7.
That's one thing. I could look for the highest possible payoff and try and steer towards it.
That seems like a reasonable way of playing the game.
Not on something this simple, where you can see it obviously fails.
But in a more complex game, you might think that, look for the best outcome and try and steer towards it.
But you've got to bear in mind that your opponent is steering away from it.
Or I could look at it and say, ah, that's the 1.
I definitely want to avoid the 1, so I can't possibly steer left.
I'm trying to avoid the bad outcome, so I should go right.
Or you could look at it and say, okay, how about this entire tree?
What's the average here? What's the average goodness of steering left or right?
If you take an average on 7 and 1, you get 4.
Because 7 plus 1 is 8.
If you take the average of 3 and 5, you also get 4.
So in this case, they're the same.
Does that mean they're both equally good?
Well, no, because one of them might end up with a 1 and one of them might end up with a 3.
So we're basically saying here, okay, there are different ways to evaluate the choices that you make.
Yep, and most of them don't work.
Most of them aren't any good.
But there is one way that works, which is basically what we did, which is min-max.
And so it's a recursive function.
So let's try a more complicated game.
I'm going to generate some random numbers just using Python to get us a list and then shuffle that list.
And there it is.
So I'm just going to draw the tree in.
Before, it was obvious that I kind of designed those choices to make a point.
Here, it's random, so it's a real game now.
In many ways, a better game than knots and crosses, because somebody's going to actually win, probably.
Whenever you see a tree in computer science, you should always kind of be thinking about recursion,
which you've done a video on before, right?
So I dive back into this same piece of code.
Because a tree has this kind of fractal structure,
where ideally you want to have an algorithm where you do the same thing at every part of the tree.
So you can have one algorithm that processes the whole tree.
So the problem with recursion, a problem with recursion, is infinite recursion,
where you have this sort of loop of nested stuff that never ends.
You need a degenerate case.
You need a case where the answer is easy.
And in this case, it's the bottom, right?
So if we are at the bottom, first move by the maximizing player,
second move by the minimizing player, third move by the maximizing player.
So here, which way should I go?
I should go with whichever one is bigger.
It's the 7, right?
So we can effectively call this a 7.
It's not the end of the game, but the value of this node is effectively 7,
because if this player directs us to there, the game will end with a 7.
So you can do that in each case.
So this one is a 5, because that's the bigger one.
This one is a 3, and this one is the 6.
So now these nodes, which before you couldn't do because they didn't have any values,
now these look a lot like the nodes below.
So here, now we're being the minimizing player,
so this will be a 5, and this will be a 3.
And now we're being the maximizing player again, who wants to go for the 5.
So you can see here that as the maximizing player, the best score I can get is the 5.
That's assuming that we're all playing by the same decision-making structure, right?
Yes. It helps that it's the optimal decision-making structure in this situation.
Okay.
But you don't have to make the best choice, right?
If you make a mistake, I have values on all the other nodes of the tree.
I can make, probably do even better.
But the way that min-max works is you end up with making the best possible play you could make as bad as possible.
And you're trying to do the same to me.
This is a game you can play with your friends.
It's a huge fun for everyone.
If you can do min-max in your head, and obviously if you have,
you can put 16 numbers at the bottom, 32, whatever.
But you'll notice, of course, the more numbers you have at the bottom,
the more work you've got to do to figure out all of these intervening nodes.
And it's tractable for some real games that people play, like Noughts and Crosses.
So I could, I'm going to try it.
So you take a game like Noughts and Crosses, tic-tac-toe,
which is so simple that human beings reliably learn to play it optimally.
You start off at the beginning, your Noughts.
You have nine choices, right?
Because you can go 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
Those are your options.
Now it's the Crosses' turn, and there you have eight options,
because one of the squares is taken.
So 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
And here there's 8, and you see, just quickly this becomes ridiculous.
But no game of Noughts and Crosses lasts more than nine turns.
Guaranteed, you run out of spaces.
We go along, blah, I'm only going to fill in part of the tree now.
The point is, what's the degenerate case?
Because we're not trying to get numbers.
So what you do is, you say, this isn't going to be right.
But let's just say, as an example, for a moment, yes, that it's that.
So it's a win for Noughts.
So if we're playing Noughts, we give this board a score of 1,
because we say, 1, we've won. Excellent.
A different board, where the Crosses have a win,
that's a minus 1, because I really don't want that.
And then any state where the game is over, but nobody's won,
it's surprisingly difficult.
I accidentally won it.
This is how hard this game is.
There. What can I do? All I do is win.
So, uh...
So, okay, that's a draw, yeah?
That's a draw. So that's a 0.
If it's your turn, and you have a move that can win,
then that board state is a win.
And therefore, you just propagate that up indefinitely,
exactly the same way as you would before.
Yeah, so you can see how you can plot this out.
And it's much too big to actually do.
But if you write a computer program to do it, it's not difficult.
It's a short program. It doesn't take long to run.
And Noughts and Crosses is a solved game, right?
So, let's draw the thing for chess.
Chess. How much paper have we got?
Yeah, let's draw chess.
Okay.
Yeah.
I'm not going to draw chess.
Why are you not going to draw chess?
Why, you know, it can't be that much more difficult, can it?
Yeah, so we need more paper.
We need a lot more paper to draw chess.
And the issue is, the thing you can see,
the thing that's so different here,
between the simple game, the very simple game,
and Noughts and Crosses,
is this thing called branching factor,
which is, basically, at each little node,
how many branches does the tree have?
Simple. In this game, it's two.
Here we have two choices. Here we have two choices.
Here we have two choices. You always have two choices.
This is a longer game.
It has more turns.
But the branching factor is still two.
Every turn, you have two choices you can make.
In Noughts and Crosses, okay,
firstly, it's more complicated because the branching factor is higher.
Secondly, it's complicated because it changes.
In the first turn,
you have nine choices.
The second turn, you have eight, and so on.
So the branching factor actually reduces
as the game goes on,
which is one of the things that makes it easier to compute.
So let's think about it.
Let's think about chess, then.
In chess, the very beginning, let's say,
you're white, you're about to start.
You've got eight pawns you can move.
You can move them forward one.
So that's eight possibilities.
You've got two.
So that's 16, plus you have
two knights that are allowed to move
because they can jump, so
each of those has two. It's another four.
I think it's 20. I don't really play chess.
But I think it's 20. I think you start off with 20.
So I would be drawing 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7,
8, 9, 10, 11, 12, all the way up to 20.
And then, as the game goes on,
much like in Noughts and Crosses,
the number of possible moves
available to you, legal moves,
varies, right?
So presumably first it goes up?
Yeah. As the game opens up
early on, you get more moves
available because you've got sort of more
space and things can
move to several different
positions and all of that kind of thing.
And then
past a certain point, it starts
to go down again because pieces get
captured. And obviously
when you have only a few pieces
on the board, you don't have as many moves
available to you. But on
average, when people play chess,
I think the average
branching factor is about 35.
But chess games
generally go longer than
9 turns, right? So
when you're calculating the number
of nodes in your tree,
every turn
you're multiplying by the branching factor
and that quickly gets
completely unmanageable. So you can't
just min-max on chess like this.
It's computationally
completely
infeasible.
Which is why chess was considered
such a big milestone
for a long time. If you could make a computer that could play
chess, you know, you're not just doing this
very trivial brute forcing
thing like you're doing for naughts and crosses.
If a computer could play chess
it would really have to be thinking, right? You can see
how here we were taking the
end states where we knew the value
of the game and then propagating backwards
in time from there to
give value to these board states that we didn't
know the value of before. The problem is there
you have to go right from the very end of the game
which in chess you can't
do. There's just too many possibilities.
So you need
some way of giving boards
values that isn't just
propagating backwards from the possibilities
from known and, you know, checkmate states.
And
luckily in chess there's a lot of things you can do
about that. The most obvious
one is just
counting up the pieces.
You just say, well a pawn is worth
you know, one point and a queen
is worth nine. You do some analysis
of how games tend to go
and you try and figure out
how good the pieces you have left are, basically.
And the position of them obviously is important
but you can
get a good, it's a good heuristic.
It's a good approximation
to just add up the
scores of the pieces and say
well, you know, this team
has both their
knights and still has their
queen and this only has one
knight and has lost their queen so
it's really obvious that this team is winning.
And therefore that's a good state
of the board and you don't need to be able to see
all the way to the endgame to know
that it's a good state of the board. So the point is
because chess's branching factor is so much higher
you can't do this thing where
you work backwards from the end states.
Because the branching factor is too high.
You have to start from where you are
and look forwards and say
okay, hypothetically, if I went this way
what would that look like? What boards
would that allow me to get to? And then
if from there I went here, how would that look?
And so on. You don't know whether you're
heading towards a win or not. And this is
where the heuristics come in, is that
they let you put some kind of
numbers on these nodes. Like,
you know, do I still have my queen in this node?
And that should guide you towards
winning positions because there tend to be
more winning positions in situations where you have your queen.
But it's always a heuristic.
They're not
the chess AI is not
seeing forwards in time to a win.
They're seeing forwards a certain distance
and seeing that it's a good position to be in
according to. And obviously it's not
just what they have on the board. Like, that's an oversimplification.
There's a lot of
different heuristics. But the point is
you're going to have to evaluate
a very, very large number of boards.
So you want something you can compute
quickly. Because the more boards you can
evaluate, the further ahead you can look.
And therefore the better you can play
even in this game. If you're
playing with someone and you can think
more moves ahead than them,
that gives you a huge advantage because you can force
them into a situation where
the best move available to them is quite bad.
And they didn't think to steer
away from that because they didn't look as far ahead as you.
What this number means is, if I
go here and then play
perfectly from that point on, what's the
worst score I'd end up getting? This algorithm
assumes that your opponent is always going to
play the best move that's
available to them. Because you're
always prepared for the worst possible scenario.
So you're only ever pleasantly surprised.
Chess is a different ballgame.
It's got more complicated manoeuvres.
It's got different ways of branching
as well as larger branches.
So, how does this all feed back into
our original point of, go looks pretty straightforward
to me. Right.
Okay, go. Right.
Let's draw go.
Okay, we're
going to need more paper
and a significantly larger universe
to put that paper in.
Go is difficult for a lot of reasons actually.
The first reason that makes
go difficult is the branching factor
is very high. It's generally
more than 200
compared to
Chess's 35.
So every turn
there are at least
200 possible moves you could be making.
And so
if you imagine me drawing this tree with
200. Come on then, let's draw it.
Alright, let's do it.
200. 1, 2, I'm going to run out of pen.
2, 3,
4, I'm going to go in between.
5, 6, 7, 39, 40,
41, 42. Do you know what?
I think life's too short, Rob.
Yeah, no, you're right.
Yeah, this margin is too narrow to contain.
It's not going to happen, right?
It's not going to happen.
And what's more,
even, you know, it wasn't going to happen
with noughts and crosses, but you can do it in a computer.
You can't do that with go.
You can't do that with chess, even.
And you really can't do it with go.
And so even a lot of the cleverness
of tree search
and pruning
and all of the really neat
algorithmic
improvements people have made
for ways of navigating these trees
that allow
this type of old-fashioned
AI to be extremely good
at playing chess, better than any human
at this point,
that approach is not going to work
with go and was
never going to work with go. And so
go became
the great, oh my god, past tense,
go became the great
the great milestone,
right, after chess, go was
the big one. So, right,
we're going with, why is it so hard?
The branching factor
is huge. That's one
thing. But also
you don't have a lot
of the tricks that you have with chess.
You can glance at a chessboard,
as I said, and just add up the pieces and say,
well, this, you know, white is probably winning or black
is probably winning. In go,
that's not the case. In
the middle of a game of go, between
two good players, other good
players could not necessarily
tell you who's winning right now.
Because the specifics of who's
winning depends very sensitively on
the precise
layout of the pieces. It's not
just a matter of who has more stones on the
board or who has more
territory or who has more points
or anything like that. It's
sort of an emergent property of the
pattern, of the layout,
which means you don't have these
easy shortcuts you can use to evaluate
a position. Not only are
there ten times as many
possibilities to search, there's
no obvious way to even
tell if a position is good once you're
looking at it. Which is, well, this is
why this is so impressive, what's been achieved
by AlphaGo.
To beat the best human players
at a game where
all of the standard
tricks of the trade won't
work, and you have to
really try something new.