So, before we were talking about AI risk and AI safety and just trying to lay out in a
very generalized sort of way how general artificial intelligence can be dangerous and some of
the type of problems it could cause and just introducing the idea of AI safety or AI alignment
theory as an area of research in computer science.
And we also talked about super intelligence and the kind of problems that, the unique
problems that can pose. And I thought what would be good is to bring it down to a more
concrete example of current AI safety research that's going on now and kind of give a feel
for where we are, where humanity is on figuring these problems out.
Supposing that we do develop a general intelligence, you know, an algorithm that actually implements
general intelligence, how do we safely work on that thing and improve it? Because the
situation with this stamp collector is, it's, from its first instant, it's a super intelligence.
So we create it with a certain goal and as I said, as soon as we switch it on, it's extremely
dangerous, which people pointed out and it's true, you know, it was a thought experiment.
It's true that that's probably not what will happen, right? You'll have some significantly
weaker intelligence first that may work on improving itself or we may improve it. So
the situation where you just create the thing and then it goes off and does its own thing,
either perfectly or terribly from the beginning is unlikely. It's more likely that the thing
will be under development. So then the question is, how do you make a system which you can
teach? How do you create a system which is a general intelligence that wants things in
the real world and is trying to act in the real world but is also amenable to being corrected
if you create it with the wrong function, with the wrong utility function and you realise
that it's doing something that actually you don't want it to do, how do you make it so
that it will allow you to fix it? How do you make an AI which understands that it's unfinished,
that understands that the utility function it's working with may not be the actual utility
function it should be working with? Right, so utility function is what the AI cares about.
So the stamp collecting device, its utility function was just how many stamps in a year.
This is kind of like its measure, is it? Yeah, it's the thing that it's trying to optimise
in the world. The utility function takes in world states as an argument and spits out
a number is broadly the idea. If the world was like this, is that good or bad? And the
AI is trying to steer towards world states that are valued highly by its utility function.
You don't have to explicitly build the AI in that way but it will always, if it's behaving
coherently, it will always behave as though it's in accordance with some utility function.
Also before I talked about convergent instrumental goals, that if you have some final goal, like
make stamps, that there are instrumental goals which are the goals that you do on the way
to your final goal, right? So like acquire the capacity to do printing is like perhaps
an instrumental goal towards making stamps. But the thing is there are certain goals which
tend to pop out even across a wide variety of different possible terminal goals. So for
humans, an example of a convergent instrumental goal would be money. If you want to make a
lot of stamps or you want to cure cancer or you want to establish a moon colony, whatever
it is, having money is a good idea, right? So even if you don't know what somebody wants,
you can reasonably predict that they're going to value getting money because money is so
broadly useful. Before we talked about this, we talked about improving your own intelligence
as a convergent instrumental goal. It's another one of those things where it doesn't really
matter what you're trying to achieve. You're probably better at achieving it if you're
smarter. So that's something you can expect AIs to go for even without making many assumptions
about their final goal. So another convergent instrumental goal is preventing yourself
from being destroyed. It doesn't matter what you want to do. You probably can't do it if
you're destroyed. So it doesn't matter what the AI wants unless it wants to be destroyed
in some trivial case. But if the AI wants something in the real world and believes that
it's in a position to get that thing, it wants to be alive, not because it wants to be alive
fundamentally. It's not a survival instinct or an urge to live or anything like that.
It's a knowing that it's unable to complete its duty, would it be, almost?
Yeah, it's unable to achieve its goals if it's destroyed and it wants to achieve its
goals. So that's an instrumental value, is preventing being turned off.
And I'm guessing here where we say wants to, it's not like in the human want, it's just
a turn of phrase.
Yeah, I mean as much as anything, it's closer, actually you know I'm not even sure I would
agree. Like if you talk about most machines, you talk about that they want to whatever
and it's not that meaningful because they're not agents, they're not general intelligences.
Whereas a general intelligence, when it wants something, it wants it in a similar way to
the way that people want things. So it's such a tight analogy that it wouldn't even, I think
it's totally reasonable to say that an AGI wants something.
There's another slightly more subtle version which is closely related to not wanting to
be turned off or destroyed, which is not wanting to be changed. So if you imagine, let's say,
I mean you have kids, right? Suppose I were to offer you a pill or something you could
take and this pill will like completely rewire your brain so that you would just absolutely
love to like kill your kids, right? Whereas right now what you want is like very complicated
and quite difficult to achieve and it's hard work for you and you're probably never going
to be done, you're never going to be truly happy, right? In life, nobody is, you can't
achieve everything you want. Whereas in this case, it just changes what you want. What
you want is to kill your kids and if you do that, you will be just perfectly happy and
satisfied with life, right?
You want to take this pill?
No, I don't.
You'll be so happy though.
Yeah.
But you don't want to do it.
Because, but that's quite a complicated specific case because it directly opposes what I currently want.
It's about your fundamental values, right? And so not only will you not take that pill,
you will probably fight pretty hard to avoid having that pill administered to you. Because
it doesn't matter how that future version of you would feel. You know that right now
you love your kids and you're not going to take any action right now which leads to them
coming to harm. So it's the same thing if you have an AI that, for example, values stamps,
values collecting stamps, and you go, oh wait, hang on a second. I didn't quite do that right.
Let me just go in and change this so that you don't like stamps quite so much. It's
going to say, but the only important thing is stamps. If you change me, I'm not going
to collect as many stamps, which is something I don't want. There's a general tendency for
AGI to try and prevent you from modifying it once it's running.
I can understand that now in the context you put that.
Right. Because that's, in almost any situation, being given a new utility function is going
to rate very low on your current utility function.
Okay.
So that's a problem. If you want to build something that you can teach, that means you
want to be able to change its utility function, and you don't want it to fight you.
What we want is...
Someone to stop hammering?
Yeah.
So this has been formalized as this property that we want early AGI to have, called corrigibility.
That is to say, it's open to be corrected.