In almost any situation, being given a new utility function is going to rate very low on your current utility function.
So that's a problem.
You want to, if you want to build something that you can teach, that means
you want to be able to change its utility function, and you don't want it to fight you.
So this has been
formalized as this property that we want early AGI to have, called corrigibility.
That is to say it's open to be corrected.
It understands that it's not complete, that the utility function it's running is not the be-all and end-all.
So let's say, for example, you've got you've got your AGI. It's not a super intelligence.
It's just, you know, perhaps around human level intelligence, and it's in a robot in your lab.
And you're testing it.
But you
saw a YouTube video once that said that maybe this is dangerous. So you've thought, oh, okay,
well, we'll put a big red stop button next to it.
This is the standard approach to safety with machines. Most robots in
industry and elsewhere will have a big red stop button on them.
If it's helpful, I have a disembodied stop button.
A large...
Oh, yeah.
I happen to have a button...
Wonderful, perfect.
Of appropriate type.
So, we have...
So, right, there you go.
Right, so...
So...
If only Hal would have been fitted with...
Yeah.
Sorry, Dave, I...
Can't do that, Dave.
Yes, you can.
Except, yeah, no, probably not.
I know that you and Frank
were planning to disconnect me.
And I'm afraid that's
something I cannot allow to happen.
Hal was an incorrigible design.
Is this the point we're kind of making?
Kind of. You've got your big stop button
because you want to be safe.
You understand, you know, AI is dangerous.
And the idea is if the AI starts to
do anything that maybe you don't want
it to do, you'll smack the button.
Make the buttons, like, mount it on its chest.
Something like that, you know.
So you create the thing.
You set it up with a goal.
And it's the same basic type of machine
as the stamp collector, but less powerful
in the sense it has a goal, a thing that
it's trying to maximize, and
in this case, you know, it's in a little
robot body so that it can tootle around your lab
and do things.
So you want it
to get you a cup of tea just as a test, right?
So you set it up with this goal.
You manage to specify in the AI's ontology
what a cup of tea is
and that you want one to be
in front of you. You switch it on
and it, you know, looks around,
gathers data, and it says, oh yeah, there's a kitchen
over there. It's got a kettle and it's got tea bags
and this is, like, the easiest way for me to
fulfill this goal with the body I have
now and everything set up
is to
go over there and make a cup of tea.
So far we're doing very well, right?
So it starts driving over
but then, oh no,
you forgot, it's
bring your adorable baby to the lab
day, or something, and then
and there's a kid in the way.
Your utility function only
cares about tea,
right? So it's not going to avoid
hitting the baby.
So you rush over there to hit the button
obviously, as you built it in
and what happens, of course, is that
the robot will not allow you to hit that button
because
it wants to get you a cup of tea
and if you hit the button, it won't get you any
tea, so this is a bad outcome.
So it's going to try and prevent you in any way possible
from shutting it down.
Um,
that's a problem.
Plausibly, it fights you off,
crushes the baby, and then
carries on and makes you a cup of tea.
And the fact that this button
is supposed to turn it off
is not in your utility function that you gave it.
So, obviously, it's going to
fight you. Okay.
That was a bad design.
Right? Assuming you're still
working on the project after the terrible accident,
you have another go at trying to improve things, right?
And rather than read any
AI safety research, what you do is just
come up with the first thing that pops into your head
and you say, okay,
let's add in some reward
for the button
so that
because what it's looking at right now is it says
button gets hit, I get zero reward,
button doesn't get hit,
if I manage to stop them,
then I get the cup of tea, I get, like, maximum reward.
If you give some sort of compensation
for the button being hit, maybe it won't mind
you hitting the button.
If you give it less reward for the button being hit
than for getting tea,
it will still fight you.
Because it will go, well, I could get five reward
for accepting you hitting the button,
but I could get ten for getting the tea,
so I'm still going to fight you.
The button being hit has to be just as good
as getting the tea, so you give it the same value.
Right?
So now you've got a new,
you've got a new, you know, version two.
You turn it on,
and what it does immediately
is
shut itself down.
Because that's so much quicker and easier
than going and getting the tea,
and gives exactly the same reward,
why would it not just immediately
shut itself down?
So you've accidentally made, like, a dramatically suicidal robot.
We're kind of back to the
three laws of robotics again,
but could you presumably say,
well, the robot's not allowed to shut itself down
or something like this?
Right, yeah.
So it's still a reward if it does,
so it's not going to fight you,
but it's not allowed to do it itself.
I'm guessing that's a possibility.
The robot cares about things in the real world,
and the button, whether it's pushed or not,
has a big effect on the things
that the robot cares about.
Which means that the robot cares about the button.
So either it's trying to stop you
from pressing the button,
or it's trying to press the button.
Either way, that's not what you want.
So suppose then you don't
mount the button on its chest
where it can hit it, right?
You put the button
somewhere only you can hit it.
Somehow you manage to
completely isolate the
bot from the button.
It's a fingerprint scanner or something.
Yeah, it's something that it can't do itself.
Right?
It still either wants to press the button
or wants the button not to be pressed,
but now the only path is through you.
So it's now
incentivized to manipulate you,
to deceive you, to lie to you
in some way,
either to cause you to not press it
or to cause you to press it.
If you somehow manage to persuade it,
it's not allowed to interact with the button itself.
So in the case where
it wants the button not to be pressed,
it has a reason
to deceive you. So in this example,
it would steer around the baby.
It would avoid the baby.
Assuming it has basic level of intelligence
to know you don't
want it to hit the baby, and moreover
if you realize your mistake,
you will hit the button,
shut it down, and change it,
which it doesn't want.
So it will behave as though
there's a term which
I like to use here.
I'm not sure if I should just use it because it's my own,
which is that
it will Volkswagen you.
That it will
set itself up so that it
behaves properly in the testing
environment, despite the
fact that it actually
shouldn't pass the test.
You're testing it to see
if it avoids running over babies.
So you're
trying to see does it care about
harming humans, but actually
all it cares about is you not hitting the button.
And so
then you might end up in a situation
in which
you become convinced that
the thing is perfectly safe because it keeps
passing all of your moral puzzles and tests
that you give it, but actually it's just
has enough of an understanding of your
psychology to tell what it
thinks you've put in and what it wants.
Or what you want, rather.
So it will
for as long as that
button is able to shut it down,
it will continue to attempt to deceive
you until it's in a situation in which
it believes it can't be shut down, and
then you have a problem. On the other side,
if you accidentally make something that wants
the button to be hit but is unable to,
it is going to try
and manipulate you into pressing the button.
So if you create your thing, you say
okay, make me
a cup of tea. If the button is hit,
shut yourself down.
You aren't allowed to shut yourself down.
You aren't allowed to hit the button.
But if the button is hit, the reward you get
is just as good as getting the tea,
so that you don't have a preference.
This machine really wants
to hit its own button, because that's as good as
getting the tea. So what it's likely to do,
probably, is just take a swing at you,
or something, just immediately, because
if it can quickly persuade you to hit the button,
if scaring you into hitting the button
is easier than getting the tea,
it'll just do that instead.
Which is a really kind of
unexpected outcome,
that you've made this thing with perfectly reasonable
sounding rewards, and what it
does immediately is try to
terrify you.
It reminds me of the proverbial carrot and a stick.
This is almost like, this is the
stick, and actually we need to find what
the carrot is. Would that be a fair thing to say?
Yeah, yeah. You want it
to actually want...
It's interesting,
because it has to
not care about whether
the button is pressed, right?
Because it has to take no steps
to try and cause the button to be pressed,
and take no steps to try and prevent the button
from being pressed, but nonetheless
really care that the button
exists.
So one thing that you can do,
something slightly more sensible,
is
you define the utility function
such that the whole
part of what it's really
trying to achieve in the world,
the end of the part about
paying attention to the button being pressed and
turning itself off, and it
sets it up so that those,
it adds an adjustment term
so that those are always exactly equal.
However much
value it would get
from either it being pressed or it not being pressed,
it normalises those so that it's
always completely indifferent
to whether the button is being pressed, it just doesn't care.
So that way it will never try
and hit the button on its own, it will never
prevent you from hitting the button. That's the idea.
That's a
fairly sensible approach, it has some of
its own problems.
It sounds like a really
complicated thing to evaluate, to be honest.
Yeah, firstly, yeah, it is kind of tricky
and you have to get it right, but
that's always
part of this. But one thing that's interesting
about that is that it isn't
what's called sub-agent stable.
So this is
something that is a desirable
property, and it's part of corrigibility in fact,
which is that
the, if there's
some property that the agent has,
you want
it to, if it makes any
new agents, that they
will have this property as well.
So you get some of that
for nothing, like, in the same way that you
don't want to take a pill that will
make you want to kill your kids,
you also don't want to make a clone of yourself
that wants to kill your kids, right? If you're making another
instance of yourself, or you're
creating some agent, you want
it to want what you want.
This is like the usual classic Disney
way out of a problem
for a baddie character where they go,
I'm not allowed to do this, but that doesn't mean I can't get
this person to do this for me.
I need a young pair of legs and a strong
back to go in after it.
Exactly. So in general, when
an AI designs a
successor, it will design it with the same
utility function as it has
for the same reason. But
unlike with some safety measures
where the AI will be
explicitly motivated to
remove the safety measures, if it can,
by making new agents which don't follow them,
in this case, it doesn't care.
So you might think, well, you're okay then,
it doesn't care, it won't remove the safety precautions,
but it also won't put in any effort
to keep them.
So if it's making a new version and it would
take a couple of extra seconds to put in,
oh, and also respond appropriately to the button,
and it could do anything else with that time
or those resources, it just won't do it.
Because it looks at the utilities and says,
if the button is pressed,
I get X utility. If the button isn't pressed,
I get exactly the same utility.
This bit of code does nothing, there's no point in it.
So it's going to be optimising itself,
or optimising its successor
in a way that,
yeah, it thinks is
being streamlining, potentially,
but actually it's missing the point of...
And that's kind of unavoidable.
If you give...
If you have a situation in which it wants to preserve the button
so that it can be pressed
because it wants that, then you've made something that wants
the button to be pressed and will try and manipulate you.
If you do it the other way,
you know, whichever way you do it,
you have problems. Another thing that people
have thought, you know,
as a suggestion of something you might try in this situation,
is to just have
the robot, have the AI not
know about the button.
Oh, so keep it a secret. Right, you have it hidden
somewhere, you know, the machine
is being observed from somewhere else
and they have the button
and so it's outside of their control
and they don't
even know the button exists. So they're not going
to be motivated to try and deceive you because
they're not aware that you have the capacity
to shut them down and change them.
There are a few different variants on this.
But
at the core of the problem there, you've got
the fact that you're building a general
purpose machine
to learn and reason about the real
world of uncertain
abilities, I suppose.
I mean, even
very
simple optimization systems
consistently surprise people.
And so
the idea that you could reliably
keep
such a thing, a secret, indefinitely
and it would never put two and two
together. In fact, while you're
improving it
and training it, it's going to be learning about human
psychology because that's important for the final
goal. It needs to understand
humans in order to understand
what humans want in order to do what humans want.
So the idea that it's never going to think
oh, interesting
these guys, you know, they
don't seem to trust me, I'm aware there is
this concept of an off button
and it's weird that they haven't given me one
so maybe they have
actually and just not told me about it.
That kind of hypothesis shouldn't take
too long to occur.
And of course,
if you've designed the thing in an incorrigible way
it won't let you
know that it's figured out that you have an off button
and will just deceive you as it always had.
So that's the kind of thing
which could work
but it's not really a reliable
solution. The other thing that
people sometimes suggest
and this happens
in conversations
sometimes is that people keep
applying patches.
You have a bad idea
for a way to do this and then
somebody points out the way that would
go wrong and then rather than realise
that the core approach is flawed
you apply a patch. You say
oh, well, we'll also add a negative term
for doing that and then also
for doing that, you know.
A spaghetti code ensues.
Yeah, and what's more, you're then
in a situation in which you've got this
system that you believe you've
patched every possible way.
It's kind of
you haven't
proved it's safe, you've just proved that you
can't figure out how it's dangerous
but
what are
the chances that you've genuinely thought
of every possibility?
Ideally, we really want to be able to formally
prove that the system has these properties.
You don't want a system in which
you've blocked off loads
of specific actions that the AI can do
and you're just
relying on it.
It's like running a complicated search, trying
to figure out a way to screw you over
and you're pretty sure you've blocked off all the angles.
You've kind of failed
before you've begun there, that your code is
running this extensive search
that you just hope fails
and if it finds any way
to do it, it will jump on that opportunity.
It's not a good way of going about things.
The other point about this
is that the button
is
a toy problem.
It's a simplification that's useful
for thought experiments because it lets you
express your, you know, it lets you formalise
things quite well. You only have two
possible outcomes, you hit the button or you don't hit the button.
But in fact,
with Corrigibility, what we want is a more
complex range of behaviours.
We want it to actually assist
the programmers in
its own development.
If it has, you know, it has
some understanding of its own operation,
you want it to be able to
actually point out your mistakes to you
or seek out
new information, perhaps.
If you say something ambiguous, rather than
just assuming, to say, well, do you mean this
or do you mean this?
If you believe that you've been programmed poorly,
to actually draw
the programmer's attention to what may be
the mistake, rather than, like, quietly
storing that away for
any time that they might try and press this
button on you, you know. Likewise, wanting
to maintain and repair the safety systems
and so on, these are
more
complicated behaviours than just not stopping
you from pressing the button and not trying to manipulate
you into not pressing
the button. So,
there are some things that might
work as solutions for
this specific case, but you would
hope that a really good solution
to the off-button problem
would, if you run it
in a more complicated scenario, also produce
these good, more complicated behaviours
in that situation.
So that's part of why
there are some things that maybe are solutions
to this problem, but they're not.
They're only solutions to this
specific instance of the problem, rather than
the general issue we're trying to deal with.
Right now,
we have a few different
proposals
for ways to
create
AGI with these properties,
but none
of them are without problems.
None of them seems to
perfectly solve
all of these properties in a way that
we can be really confident of.
So, this is
considered an open problem.
So,
I kind of like
this as a place to go
from the previous thing, because
I think it gives people a feel for
where we
are,
the types of problems
that, it seems like
the simplest thing in the world, right?
You've got a robot with a button. How do you make
it not stop you from hitting
the button, but also not try and persuade
you to hit the button?
That should be
easy,
and doesn't seem like it is.
So, utility function is
what the
AI cares about.
So, the stamp collecting device,
its utility function was just how many stamps
in a year.
This is kind of like its measure, is it?
Yeah, it's the thing
that it's trying to optimise.