Today I thought I'd talk about a paper fairly recent was last year a paper called concrete problems in AI safety
Which is going to be related to the stuff I was talking about before with the stop button
It's got a bunch of authors mostly from Google brain
Google's AI research
Department I guess well a lot of its AI research, but specifically Google brain
and
Some people from Stanford and Berkeley and open AI and whatever. It's a collaboration between a lot of different authors
The idea of the paper is trying to lay out a
Set of problems that we are able to currently make progress on like
If we're concerned about this far-off sort of super intelligence stuff
Sure, it seems important and it's interesting and difficult and whatever but it's quite difficult to sit down and actually do anything about it
Because we don't know
Very much about what a super intelligence will be like or how it would be implemented or whatever
the idea of this paper is that it
It lays out some problems that we can tackle now which will be helpful now and
That I think will be helpful later on as well with more advanced AI systems and making them safe as well
It lists five problems avoiding negative side effects
which is quite closely related to the stuff we've been talking about before with the stop button or the stamp collector a lot of the
Problems with that can be framed as negative side effects
They do the thing you ask them to but in the process of doing that they do a lot of things that you don't want
Them to this is like the robot running of the baby, right?
Yeah
Any anything where it does the thing you wanted it to like it makes you the cup of tea or it collects you stamps or?
Whatever but in the process of doing that it also does things you don't want it to do
So those are your negative side effects
so that's the first of the
The research areas is how do we avoid these negative side effects?
Then there's avoiding reward hacking which is about systems gaming their reward function doing something which technically counts
But isn't really what you intended the reward function to be
There's a lot of different ways that that can manifest
but this is like this is already a common problem in machine learning systems where you come up with your your
Evaluation function or your reward function or whatever your objective function and
The system very carefully optimizes to exactly what you wrote and then you realize what you wrote isn't what you meant
Scalable oversight is the next one. It's a problem that human beings have all the time
Anytime you've started a new job, you don't know what to do and you have someone who does who's supervising you the question is
What questions do you ask and how many questions do you ask because current machine learning systems?
Can learn pretty well if you give them a million examples, but you don't want your robot to ask you a million questions
You know you want it to only
Ask a few questions and use that information efficiently to learn from you safe exploration is the next one
Which is about well about safely exploring the range of possible actions
So you will want the system to experiment, you know, try different things try out different approaches
That's the only way it's gonna find what's gonna work
But there are some things that you don't want it to try even once like the baby, right, right
Yeah, you don't want it to say know what happens if I run over this baby. Do you want certain possible?
Things that it might consider trying to actually not try at all
Because you can't afford to have them happen even once in the real world like the thermonuclear war option
What happens if I do this you don't want it to try that. Is that the sort of thing? Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, yeah
It runs through a simulation of every possible type of nuclear war right but it does it in simulation
You want your system not to run through every possible type of thermonuclear war in real life to find out it doesn't work because
You can't it's too
Unsafe to do that even once the last area to look into is robustness to distributional shift
Yeah
yeah, it's it's a it's a
Complicated term, but the concept is not it's just that
the situation can change over time so
You may end up you may make something you train it
It performs well, and then things change to be different from the training scenario and that is inherently
Very difficult like it's something humans again human struggle with you find yourself in a situation
You've never been in before
but the difference I think or one of the useful things that humans do is
notice that there's a problem a lot of current machine learning systems if you if something changes underneath them and they're
Their training is no longer useful. They have no way of knowing that so they continue being just as confident in their answers that now
Make no sense
Because they're not they haven't noticed that there's a change. So
If we can't make systems that can just react to completely unforeseen circumstances
We may be able to make systems that at least can recognize that they're in
Unforeseen circumstances and ask for help and then maybe we have a scalable supervision
Situation there where they recognize the problem, and that's when they ask for help
I suppose a simplified simplistic example. This is when you have an out-of-date sack now and
It doesn't seem to realize that you happen to be doing 70 miles an hour over a plowed field
Right because somebody else's, you know built a road there
Yeah
Exactly the general tendency of unless you program them specifically not to to just plow on with what they think they should be doing
yeah can cause problems and in a
large scale
Heavily depended on you know in this case. It's your sat-nav
So it's not too big of a deal because it's not actually driving the car and you know
What's wrong and you can ignore it whatever as AI systems become more important and more integrated into everything that kind of thing can
Become a real problem
Yeah, yeah
Yeah, so it the way the way it does all of these is it
Gives a quick outline of what the problem is
They the example they usually use is a cleaning robot like we've made this we've made a robot
It's in an office or something and it's cleaning up and then it they sort of frame the different problems
There's things that could go wrong in that scenario
So it's pretty similar to the get me a cup of tea and don't run over the baby type setup
It's clean the office and don't you know, knock anything over or destroy anything and then for each one
The paper talks about possible approaches to each problem and
Things we can work on basically things that we don't know how to do yet
But which seem like they might be doable in a year or two and some careful thought this paper
Is this one for me? Yeah, it's really good. It's
It doesn't cover anything like the range of the problems in AI safety
But of the problems specifically about avoiding accidents because all of these are problem all of these are ways of
creating possible accidents
Right possible causes of accidents
There's all kinds of other problems. You can have an AI that don't fall under accidents
But within that area, I think it covers everything and it's quite readable. It's quite
It doesn't require really high level because it's an overview paper doesn't require high level AI
Understanding for the most part anyone can read it and it's on the archive
So, you know, it's freely available these guys now working on AI safety. They do is this then they've hung their hats up
They've written a paper and they're hoping someone else is going to sort it all out for them
Yeah, these people are working on AI safety right now
But they're not the only people this paper was released in summer of 2016. So it's been about a year since it came out
and
Since then there have been more advances and some of the problems posed have had really interesting solutions
Or well not solutions early work that looks like it could become a solution or approaches new interesting ideas about
Ways to tackle these problems. So I think as a paper
It's already been successful in spurring new research and giving people a focus to build their AI safety research on top of
So we just need to watch this space, right? Yeah, exactly
And there's a kid in the way your
utility function only cares about
Tea, right? So it's not going to avoid hitting the baby
So you rush over there to hit the button obviously as you built it in and what happens of course is that the robot?