While back we were talking about
The stop button problem, right? You have this you have this
It's kind of a toy problem in AI safety. You have an artificial general intelligence in a robot
it wants something, you know, it wants to make you a cup of tea or whatever you put a big red stop button on it and
You want to set it up so that it behaves courageably that it will allow you to hit the button
It won't hit the button itself, you know, and it won't try and prevent you this sort of
Behaving in a
In a sensible way in a safe way
and
That like by default
Most AGI designs will not behave this way
Well, we left it as an open problem, right and it kind of still is an open problem
But there have been some really interesting things proposed as possible solutions or approaches to take and I wanted to talk about
cooperative inverse reinforcement learning I
I
Thought the easiest way to explain a cooperative inverse reinforcement learning is to build it up backwards, right?
learning we know like machine learning and
Reinforcement learning is an area of machine learning. I guess you could call it. It's it's kind of a
It's a way of presenting a problem
in most machine learning
The kind of thing that people have talked about already a lot on computer file
Thinking of who has videos and the related ones
Usually you get in some data and then you're trying to do something with that like classify
You know unseen things or you're trying to do like regression to find out what value something would have for a certain inputs that kind
of thing
whereas
reinforcement learning the idea is you have an agent in an environment and
you're trying to find a
Policy but so so
Let's back up. What do we mean by an agent? It's an entity that interacts with its environment
To try and achieve something effectively. It's doing things in an environment
So this isn't that's really if is this a physical thing or is it me doesn't have to be so if you have
Robot in a room then you can model that as the robot being an agent and the room being environment. Similarly if you have a
computer game like
Pac-man
Then Pac-man is an agent and the sort of maze he's in is his environment
So let's stick with Pac-man that the way that a reinforcement learning
Framework for dealing with Pac-man is you say? Okay, you've got Pac-man. He's the agent. He's in the environment and you have
Actions the Pac-man can take in the environment now, it's kind of neat in Pac-man
There are always exactly four actions you can take or well
I guess five you can sit there and do nothing. You can move up left right or down
You don't always have all of those options like sometimes there's a wall and you can't move, right?
but those are the only that's the that's the complete set of actions that you have and
Then you have the environment contains sort of dots that you can pick up
Which are they give you points?
It's got these ghosts that chase you that you don't want to touch and I think there's also there's like pills you can pick
Up that make the ghosts edible and then you chase them down and stuff
Anyway, so the difference in reinforcement learning is that the agent is in the environment and it learns by interacting with the environment
It's and so it's kind of close to the way that animals learn and the way that humans learn
You try you try doing something, you know, I'm gonna try, you know touching this fire. Oh that hurt
So that's that's caused me like a negative reward. That's caused me a pain signal, which is something
I don't want so I learn to avoid doing things like touching a fire
so in in a pac-man environment, you might you might sort of say
If you're in a you're in a situation like let's draw pac-man. Let's say he's in a maze like this
You look at pac-man's options
He can't go left. He can't go right he can go up and if he goes up
He'll get a dot which earns you some points
So up gets a score of you know, plus 10 or however, you've decided it
Or well, whatever the score is in the game either way or if he goes down he'll be immediately got by this ghost
The point is that pac-man doesn't need to be aware of the entire board right of the entire maze
you can just feed in a fairly small amount of information about his immediate environment, which is the same thing as
If you have a robot in a room, it can't it doesn't know everything about the whole room
it can only see what it sees through its camera, you know, it has
Sensors they give it some some information about the environment
partial information I
Suppose just playing devil's advocate. The difference here is usually pac-man is being controlled by a human who can see the whole board
So the point being if that ghost is actually not static and is chasing pac-man and he's heading up to get that
pill if
If a few pixels later that that corridor if you like stops in a dead end
Yep, well, he's kind of stuffed either way really that's true. Yeah, so that is because so so
most
Well, yeah, almost every
Reinforcement learning algorithm almost everything that tries to deal with this problem
Doesn't just look at the immediate surroundings or it looks at the immediate surroundings, but it also looks a certain distance in time
So you're not just saying what's going to happen next frame, but
So like if you if you go down
Here most algorithms would say okay the option of going down in this situation is bad
But also all of the options we chose in all of the situations that we were in in the last
Second or two also get a little bit. This is kind of a decay. There's time time discounting
so that
You're not just punishing the immediate thing that causes the negative reward
But also the decisions you make leading up to it so that pac-man might learn not to get himself stuck in corners
As well as just learning not to run straight into ghosts
so
That's the basics of reinforcement learning. There's different algorithms that do it and the idea is you
You actually you start off exploring the environment just at random
You just pick completely random actions and then as those actions start having consequences for you and you start getting rewards and punishments
You start to learn
Which actions are better to use in which situations does that mean that in pac-man's case would learn the maze
Or would it just learn the better choices? It depends on what algorithm you're using
Very sophisticated one might learn the whole maze a simpler one might just learn
More kind of local policy
But
The point is yeah
You learn you learn a kind of mapping between or a function that takes in the situation you're in and outputs a good
action to take
There's also kind of an interesting trade-off there which I think we may have talked about before about
exploration versus exploitation in that
you want your agent to be generally taking good actions, but
You don't want it to always take the action that it thinks is best right now because it's understanding may be incomplete and then it
Just kind of gets stuck right? It never finds out anything. It never finds out anything about other
Options that it could have gone with because as soon as it did something that kind of worked
It just goes with that forever. So a lot of these systems build in some
Some variance some randomness or something, right?
Exactly, like you usually do the thing you think is best but some small percentage of the time you just try something random anyway
And you can change that over time like a lot of algorithms as as the
Policy gets more and more as they learn more and more they start doing random stuff less and less
That kind of thing. So that's the like absolute basics of reinforcement learning and how it works and it's really really powerful
like
Especially when you combine it with deep neural networks as the thing that's doing the learning
Deep mind did this really amazing thing where I think they were playing pac-man
They were playing a bunch of different Atari games and the thing that's cool about it is
All they told the system was here's what's on the screen and here's the score of the game
Make the score be big the score is your reward, right? That's it and it learned
All of the specific dynamics of the game and generally achieved
Top level human or superhuman play the next word is going to be inverse
We did a thing with who they on anti learning, but can't work all the time. That's what the thing, right?
Yeah, this is not like that. This is a description of a different type of problem
it's it's a totally different problem that they call inverse because
in reinforcement learning
you have a reward function that determines when you what situations you get rewards in and
you're in your environment with your reward function and you're trying to
Find the appropriate actions to take that maximize that reward
in inverse reinforcement learning
You're not in the environment at all. You're watching an expert
so you've got the video of the world championship record pac-man player, right and
You have all of that all of that information you can see
So you're saying?
Rather than rather than having the reward function and trying to figure out the actions
You can see the actions and you're trying to figure out the reward function
So it's inverse because you're kind of solving the reverse of the problem. You're not trying to
maximize a reward
By choosing actions, you're looking at actions and trying to figure out what reward they're maximizing
So that's really useful because it lets you sort of learn by observing experts
So coming back to AI safety, you might think that this would be kind of useful
From an AI safety perspective, you know
You have this problem the core problem of AI safety or one of the core problems of AI safety is
How do you make sure the AI wants what we want?
We can't reliably specify what it is we want
So and if we create something very intelligent that wants something else
That's something else is what's probably going to happen. Even if we don't want that to happen. How do we make a system that?
Reliably wants the same thing we want
so you can see how inverse reinforcement learning might be kind of attractive here because
You might have a system that watches humans doing things and tries to figure out, you know
If we are experts at being humans, it's trying to figure out what rewards we're maximizing and try and sort of formalize in its
In its understanding what it is we want by observing us, that's pretty cool
But yeah, it has some problems one problem is that we don't
In inverse reinforcement learning there's this assumption of
optimality
That the person that the agent you're watching is an expert and they're doing optimal play and you're you know
there is some clear coherent thing like the score that they're optimizing and
the assumption of
The the algorithms that do this is that?
The way the world champion plays is the best possible way and that assumption is obviously never quite true or generally
Not quite true
But it works well enough, you know
But
Humans are not like
Human behavior is not
Actually really optimizing to get what humans want perfectly and ways
Places where that assumption isn't true could cause problems
So is this where cooperative comes in because when we started this we're doing it backwards. It's cooperative inverse reinforcement learning, right?
So you could imagine a situation where you have the robot you have the AGI
It watches people doing their thing uses inverse reinforcement learning to try and figure out the things humans value
Sorry, try and figure out the things humans value
and
then
Adopt those values as its own, right?
The most obvious like the first problem is we don't actually want to create something that values the same thing as humans
like
If it observes that I
You know, I want a cup of tea
We want it to want me to have a cup of tea
We don't want it to want a cup of tea
But that's like if that's quite easy to fix you just say, you know
Figure out what the value is and then optimize it for the humans
Say easy to fix but you know what? I mean, it's that's doable
But then the other thing is if you're if you're trying to teach
If you're actually trying to use this to teach a robot to do something it turns out to not be very efficient
like if you
This works for Pac-man if you want to learn how to be good at Pac-man
You probably want to not just watch the world's best Pac-man player and try to copy them, right?
That's that's not like an efficient way to learn
Because there might be a situation where you used to be you're thinking
What do I do if I find myself stuck in this corner of the maze or whatever and the pros
Never get stuck there. So you have no
you have no example of what to do or all the pro all watching the pros can teach you is
Don't get stuck there. And then once you're there, you've got no
You've got no hope. Let's say I wanted to teach my robot to make me a cup of tea. I
Go into the kitchen and I show it
How I make a cup of tea I
Would probably have to do that a lot of times
to actually get the all the information across
because and
You'll notice this is not how people teach right if you were teaching a person how to make a cup of tea
You might do something like if there's some difficult stage of the process you might show you might do one demonstration
But show that one stage like three times say and you see do it like this
Let me show you that again. And then if you're using inverse reinforcement learning the system believes that you are playing optimally
Right, so it thinks that doing it three times is somehow necessary and it's trying to figure out what values like what reward you must
Be optimizing but doing it three times is
important
So that's a problem right that's where the assumption isn't true or you might want to say
okay, what you do is you get the tea out of the box here and you put it in the thing, but if
There's none in this box. You go over to this cupboard where we keep the backup supplies and you open a new box, right?
But you can't show that
the only way that
The only way that the robot can learn
To go and get the extra supplies only when this one has run out
Is if you were in a situation where that would be optimal play
So the thing has to be actually run out in order for you to demonstrate that you can't say
If the situation were different from how it is, then you should go and do this
so the other thing you might want if you're trying to teach things efficiently, you might want the AI to be
Taking an active role in the learning process, right?
You kind of want it to be like if there's if there's some aspect of it that it doesn't understand
You don't want it just sitting there
Observing you optimally do the thing and then trying to copy
If there's something that it didn't see you kind of want it to be able to say hang on
I didn't see that, you know, or I'm confused about this or maybe ask you a clarifying question or
Just in general like communicate with you and cooperate with you in the learning process
So
Yeah, so so the way that the way that cooperative inverse reinforcement learning works is it's a way of setting up the rewards
Such that these types of behaviors
Hopefully will be incentivized and should come out automatically if you're optimizing it, you know, if the AI is doing well
so what you do is you specify the interaction as a cooperative game where the
robots reward function is
the humans reward function
but
The robot doesn't know that reward function at all. It never knows
The reward that it gets and it never knows the function that generates the reward that it gets
It just knows that it's the same as the humans
So it's trying to optimize. It's trying to maximize the reward it gets
but the only
clues it has for what it needs to do to maximize its own reward is
Observing the human and trying to figure out what the human is trying to maximize
This is a bit like two players on a computer game, but you can only see one school
Yeah, like if you're you're you're both on the same team. Yeah
But only the human knows the rules of the game
Effectively you both want
You both get the same reward. So you both want the same thing just kind of by definition
but the process so in a sense you've kind of just defined the core problem of as I was saying that the core problem one
of the core problems of AI safety is
How do you make sure that the robot wants what the human wants and in this case you've just specified it usually you couldn't do
That because we don't really know what the human wants either
Two people who don't speak the same language can still communicate
With actions and gestures and things. Yeah, and you can generally get the gist of the idea across to the other person
Is it a bit like that? Yeah, but a sufficiently sophisticated agent
If you have an AGI that could be quite powerful
It can speak, you know, and it can understand language and everything else and it knows
that
That so it knows for example
Hopefully it should be able to figure out that
When the human is showing something three times
That it's that the human is doing that in order to communicate information and not because it's the optimal way to do it
because it knows
that the human knows
There's that kind of there's common knowledge of
What's going on in this in the scenario?
so it allows for situations where the human is just demonstrating something or
Explaining something or it allows the AI to ask about things that it's unclear about
Because everybody's on the same team trying to achieve the same thing in principle
So
The point is if you have a big red stop button in this scenario
The AI is not
incentivized to disable or ignore that stop button
because
It constitutes important information about its reward
right, the AI is desperately trying to maximize a reward function that it doesn't know and
So if it observes the human trying to hit the stop button
That provides really strong information that what it's doing right now is not going to maximize the humans reward
Which means it's not going to maximize its own reward
so it wants
To allow itself to be shut off if the human wants to shut it off
Because it's for its own good
So this is this is a clever way of aligning its interests with ours, right, right?
It's not so it's so like
The the the problem in the in the default situation is I've told it to get a cup of tea and it's going to do
That whatever else I do and if I tried to turn it off
It's not going to let me because that will stop it from getting a cup of tea
whereas in this situation the fact that I want a cup of tea is something it's not completely sure of and
So it doesn't think it knows better than me
So when I go to hit that stop button it thinks oh
I thought I was supposed to be going over here and getting a cup of tea and running over this baby or whatever
But the fact that he's rushing to hit the button means I must have gotten something wrong
So I'd better stop and learn more about this situation because I'm at risk of losing a bunch of reward
So, yeah, it seems like it seems like a potentially workable thing
a workable approach
So one interesting thing about this is there is still an assumption
that the humans behavior is in accordance with some utility function or some reward function some objective function like
if the human behaves very irrationally
that can
Cause problems for this system because the whole thing
Revolves around the fact that the robot is not completely confident of what its reward is
It's got a model of its of what the reward function is like that. It's constantly updating as it learns
And it doesn't have full confidence and it's using the human as the source of information
So fundamentally the robot believes that the human knows better than it does how to maximize the humans reward
So in situations where that's not true
like if you run this for long enough and the
Robot managed to build up a really really high level of confidence in what it thinks the human reward function is
Then it might ignore its stop button later on if it thinks that
It knows better than the human what the human wants
Which sounds very scary but might actually be what you want to happen
Like if you imagine
You know, it's the it's the future and we've got these robots and they all have a big red stop button on them
and they're all you know, and
Everything's wonderful and you say to your robot. I'll take my
My four-year-old son to school, you know drive him to school in the car because it's the 1950s sci-fi future
Where it's not self-driving cars. It's like robots in cars anyway, and it's
It's driving this kid to school
It's doing 70 on the motorway and the kid sees the big red shiny button and smacks it
right in principle a human has just pressed the button and a
Lot of designs for a button would just say a human is hit your button. You have to stop whereas this design might say I
Have been around for a long time. I've learned a lot about what humans value and also I observed that this specific human
Does not reliably behave in its own best interests
So maybe this hitting the button is not communicating to me information about what this human really wants
They're just hitting it because it's a big red button and I should not shut myself off
So it has the potential to be safer than a button that always works
But it's a little bit unsettling
That you might end up with systems that sometimes actually do ignore the shutdown command because they think they know better
Because what it's looking at right now is it says button gets hit I get zero reward
Button doesn't get hit if I manage to stop them. Then I get the cup of tea. I get like maximum reward
If you give some sort of company