So I think it's worth talking a little bit because like I'm usually talking to you about AI safety
About the decision that opening I made to not release the fully trained model the big one
So because this has not been released
We know that it works like a transformer left to its own devices without being fine-tuned
It's just a massive amount of data and off you go. Is that right?
Yeah, like there's enough information given in the paper to reproduce it
and
You just need the giant giant data set, which is a real hassle to make especially because
You really need high quality data does it say anywhere in the paper about how long it took to train?
Yes
And how and how many different how many TPUs you need and stuff like that?
What's a TPU?
That's a tensor processing unit. Okay, so like a GPU but fancy
You need a lot of money if you tried to train this with just like Amazon's cloud computing offering you would be
You'd end up with a bill that I expect would be in the hundreds of thousands of pounds. Like it's a lot of compute
But with all of these things it's a lot of compute to train them. It's not that much computer run
This isn't a new architecture. This isn't like a vast breakthrough
from that perspective, it's just like the same thing, but much bigger and
And nobody else is keeping their research and like not releasing their models to the public
So, you know you think it's dangerous to say that you think that your work might be dangerous and you're not releasing it
It's kind of like you think it's much more dangerous than other people's work and therefore like it's so powerful that it's dangerous
It's kind of like you're saying that your stuff is so good that it's you know, it's too powerful for you
You know, I can't release it or whatever. I think people reacted in a sense to that
Yeah, I mean there's it's just smack a little bit of publicity stunt
I mean assuming it's not a publicity stunt assuming this is not that which I don't believe it is. What are they worried about?
So the worry like people make a big
People make a big deal of the idea of it generating fake news like fake news
Articles that will convince people that there are actually unicorns or whatever
I don't think that that's the risk
I also don't think that that's really what opening I thinks the risk is if you want to generate a fake thing
It's still not expensive to do that. You can just sit down and write something, right?
You don't need a language model to write you fake news
And in fact, you don't have that much control over it
So you would if you were trying to actually manipulate something you would want to be tweaking it
Anyway, I don't think that's the risk the the thing that
The thing that most concerns me about things like GPT to is
Like the content is not particularly good
But it is convincingly human and so it creates a lot of potential for making fake users
and
So there is this constant arms race between bot operators and the big platforms, right?
There's teams working at Google at YouTube at Facebook everywhere
Working on identifying
Accounts that aren't real and there's various ways you can do that
one of the things you can do is you can analyze the text that they write because the language models that are out there aren't
Very good. And so if some if if an account is like repeating itself a lot
Or you have a whole bunch of accounts that are all saying like exactly the same thing
Then you know that this is like a spam maybe manipulation attempt and so on
But with GPT to you can have things that produce
you give the same prompt and then you post all of the outputs and all of those outputs are different from each other and
They all look like they were written by a human
and it's not a
Human can look at them probably and figure out
Hang on a second. This doesn't quite seem right
But only if you're really really paying attention
Which
Human attention on a large scale is super expensive, right?
So much more expensive than the compute needed to generate the samples
So you're outmatched if you if you spend more they can spend it you can you can spend
Ten times more and you cripple yourself financially and they can spend ten times more and it's fine. So you're gonna lose that battle
The other thing is so so it becomes very difficult to identify fake users
the other thing is one way that you can identify fake users is
by
Analyzing the graph like the social graph or the interaction graph and you can see that
Because humans usually when they see spam posts that are full of links to dubious websites and whatever
they download them they don't reply to them and
You can create you can fake the voting metrics by having these accounts vote for each other's stuff
but then you can analyze the graph of that and say oh all of these plate people they all only vote for each other and
The people who we know are humans like never vote for them. So we assume those are all bots and we can ignore them
But the samples that GPT to produces the big model are
Convincing enough to get actual humans to engage with them, right? It's not like oh my god, that's so persuasive
I've read this article and now I believe this thing about unicorns
It's just like I believe that a real human wrote this thing and now I want to argue with them
That there aren't unicorns or whatever right and now you have real humans
engaging in actual meaningful conversation with bots and
Now you've got a real problem because how are you going to spot who the bots are?
When you can't do it automatically just by analyzing the text
You can't even do it by aggregating the human responses to them because the humans keep thinking that they're actual humans
so now you have the ability to produce large amounts of
fake users that the
Platforms can't spot and therefore they can't stop those users votes from counting on things up voting things and down voting things and liking them
and subscriptions and everything else and manipulating the metrics that way one thing people would do is
spot the
The profile pictures if you're trying to generate a large number of bots
where are you going to get your pictures from and so you can do like reverse image search and get the
Find that they're all using the same picture or they're all using pictures from the same database of facial photos or whatever
Now we have these really good generative adversarial networks that can generate good-looking faces
So that's now really difficult as well and like you can't automatically detect those
Almost by definition because the way the gams work
The discriminator is like a state-of-the-art fake face image detector and it's being fooled
like that's the whole point and if you released if somebody came up with a really reliable way of
spotting those fake images then
You can just use that as the discriminator and keep training right so not releasing their full-strength model to me feels
Very sensible in the sense that people will figure it out, right?
They publish the the science someone will find it
it is worth their while to do it to spend the money to reproduce these results, but
By not releasing it. They've bought the platforms
Several months to like prepare for this to understand what's going on
And they are of course working with them and sharing the full-strength model with selected partners people
They trust to say here's what it can do
Take a moment, you know govern yourself accordingly like get ready because this stuff is going to come but they're giving everybody a heads-up to
Mitigate the potential like negative impacts that this work might have and the other thing is it sets a really good precedent, I think
because
maybe GPG to isn't that dangerous, but
the stuff that we're making is just getting more and more powerful and
At some point somebody is going to develop something that is really dangerous and by then you want there to be accepted
practices and social norms and industry standards about
Thinking about the impact of your work before you release it
and
So it's good to start with something that like there's some argument that there could be some danger from it
just so that everybody is like aware that this is a thing that you can do and
That people won't think you're weird or you're bragging or it's a publicity stunt or whatever to make it like socially
okay to say
We found this cool result and we're not going to put it out there because we're not sure about the safety of it
And I think that that's something that's really really necessary. So I think that open AI is very smart to
Start that off now before we really really need it
Make a principled
Decision now, I want the seven. So in principle I should be going this way, right?
You would think I want to steer towards the seven
But on the other hand at this point, it's your choice. You give it some random noise and it generates an image
From that noise and the idea is it's supposed