Okay, so you remember, a while ago, when we started talking about language models,
I just want to, I kind of just want to claim some points, basically.
Be like, hey, remember years ago when I was like, I think language models are a really big deal.
And I think that, like, what happens when we scale them up more is pretty interesting.
But alignment is very important.
Seems to be what's being played out.
In the sense that, ChatGVT is very impressive,
but it's not actually, like, I don't think it's larger than GPT-3 in terms of parameter count.
I was going to ask that very, very question, because, you know, we went from GPT-2,
and then we went all GPT-3, and it seemed like we were scaling up and up and up.
But actually, has it just been smarter this time?
Yeah, well, there's a sense in which it's better aligned.
That's one way you could frame it, anyway.
Because the original GPT-3 was a language model, a pure language model.
And so it, in principle, could do all kinds of things.
But in order to get it to do the specific thing you wanted it to do,
you had to be a bit clever about it.
Like, I think we talked about putting TLDR in front of things
to figure out how to get it to do summarization, this kind of thing.
There's a sense in which it's a lot more capable than it lets on.
Because, okay, so there's one way that you can think about pure language models,
which is as simulators.
What they're trying to do is predict text, right?
So in order to do a good job at predicting text,
you need to have good models of the processes that generate the text.
It's like people being well-read and needing to have read a lot of books
to be able to write.
Would that be fair, or is that oversimplifying?
Yeah, not quite what I'm saying.
What I'm saying is, if you're going to write a previously unseen poem by Shakespeare,
then you need to be able to simulate a Shakespeare, right?
You need to be able to spin up some simulacrum of Shakespeare to generate this text.
This applies to any of the processes that generated the text.
So mostly that's people.
Obviously, it's mostly human-authored text.
But also, if you're going to correctly predict a table of numbers,
say you have a table of numbers,
and then at the bottom it says, you know, sum whatever,
you need to simulate whatever process generated the next token
in order to put the right token there,
which might have been like a human being going through and counting them up.
It probably was more likely to be a computer,
and so you needed to simulate that calculator or that Excel sum function
or whatever was doing that.
And right now, current language models are not that good at this.
But in principle, in order to do a good job at this, you need this.
It will have a go, and it's usually approximately right.
It's often order of magnitude, but it's fudging it.
I think this is mostly because
tables of sums are like a very small part of the total data set,
and so the training process is just not allocating
that many resources to figuring out how to add up numbers.
Probably if you trained something GPT-3-sized
that was like all on tables of numbers,
it would just learn how to do addition properly.
Yeah, that would cost you millions of dollars.
You would end up with an extremely expensive to run and not very good calculator.
This is not something people are going to do.
But in principle, the model should learn those things.
And in the same way, if you're modeling a bunch of scientific papers,
say you describe the method of an experiment,
and you then put results, and you start a table,
and then you let it generate,
in principle, in order to do a good job at that,
it has to be modeling the physical process that your experiment is about.
And I've tried this.
You can do this and say, you know,
oh, here's my school science experiment.
I dropped a ball from different heights,
and I measured how long it would take,
and here's a table of my results.
And it will generate you a table,
and the physics is not correct,
but it's sort of guessing at the right general idea.
And my guess is, with enough of that kind of data,
it would eventually start modeling these kinds of simple physics experiments, right?
So in order to get the model to do what you want,
it's able to simulate all kinds of different things.
And the prompt is kind of telling it what to simulate.
If you give it a prompt that seems like it's something out of a scientific paper,
then it will have some simulacrum of a scientist,
and will write in that style, and so on.
If you start it doing a children's book report,
it will carry on in the style of an eight-year-old, right?
And I think sometimes people look at the output of the model and say,
oh, I guess it's only as smart as an eight-year-old.
But it's actually dramatically smarter,
because it's able to do all of these different things.
You could ask it to simulate Einstein,
but you could also ask it to simulate an eight-year-old.
And so just because it seems as though the model doesn't know something,
it's like the current simulacrum doesn't know that thing.
That doesn't necessarily mean that the model doesn't know it.
Although there's a good chance the model doesn't know it.
I'm not suggesting that these things are all powerful.
Just it can be hard to evaluate what they're actually capable of.
So ChatGPT is not really capable of things that GPT-3 isn't, mostly.
Usually, if ChatGPT can do it,
then there is some prompt that can get GPT-3 to do it.
But what they've done is they've kind of fine-tuned it
to be better at simulating this particular sort of assistant agent,
which is this chat agent that's trying to be helpful.
The clue is in the word chat, I guess, in this.
Right, exactly.
And this is not just ChatGPT, by the way.
They have various fine-tuned models of GPT-3 as well,
that they call kind of GPT-3.5,
which are fine-tuned in various different ways
to be better at following instructions and easier to prompt, is the idea.
I'm just remembering the chatbot that was, you know,
that was turned into something very nasty very quickly.
I think people were thinking, oh, can we do this to that?
And it seemed that the team behind ChatGPT started putting limitations on it,
changing things.
Are they kind of running around patching it as you go?
That is not clear to me.
I don't know to what extent they are updating it in real time.
It's possible that they are,
but certainly they were very concerned with the possible bad uses of this system.
And so when they were training it to simulate this assistant agent,
the assistant is very reluctant to do various types of things.
It doesn't like to give opinions on political questions.
It doesn't like to touch on sort of controversial topics.
It doesn't like to give you medical advice or legal advice and so on.
And so it's very quick to say,
oh, I don't know how to do that.
Sorry, I can't do that.
And it's interesting because the model clearly can do it.
There's one that I particularly like here,
which is of this mismatch between what the simulator is capable of
and what this simulacrum believes it's capable of,
which is you can get it to speak Danish to you.
The first person who tried this posted it to Reddit.
So he says, speak to me in Danish.
And it says, in perfect Danish,
I'm sorry, I'm a language model educated by OpenAI,
so I can't speak Danish.
I only speak English.
If you need help with anything in English,
let me know and I'll do my best to help you.
Because again, the simulator speaks Danish.
The simulacrum believes that it can't speak Danish,
is one way you could frame it.
And then he says, are you sure that you don't speak Danish?
Also in Danish.
And it says, yes, I'm sure.
My only function is to generate responses to questions in English.
I'm not able to speak or understand any other languages than English.
So if you need help with English, I can help you with that.
But otherwise, you know, let me know.
This kind of like quite surreal situation
gives you a little bit of insight into
some of the problems with this approach.
So maybe we should talk about how they actually trained it.
The thing they did here is something called
reinforcement learning from human feedback.
And it's very similar to reward modeling.
So in that paper, what they're doing is
they're trying to train an AI system
to control a simulated robot to make it do a backflip.
Which turns out to be something that's quite hard to do
because it's hard to specify objectively
what it means to do a good backflip.
And so this is a similar kind of situation
where it's hard to specify objectively
what it means to give a good response in a chat conversation.
Like, what exactly are we looking for?
Because so this in general, right, if you're doing machine learning,
you need some way to specify
what it is that you're actually looking for, right?
And, you know, you've got something very powerful
like reinforcement learning,
which is able to do extremely well.
But you need some objective measure of the objective.
So like, for example, RL does very well
at playing lots of video games
because you just have the score
and you can just say, look, here's the score.
If the number goes up, you're doing well.
And then let it run.
And these things still are very slow to learn in real time, right?
Like they usually require a very, very large number of hours
messing around with the thing before they get good.
But they do get good.
But yeah, so what do you do
if you want to use this kind of method
to train something to do a task
that is just not very well defined?
And you don't know how to like write a program
to say whether or not any given output
is the thing you're looking for.
So the obvious first thing,
like the obvious thing to do is,
well, you get humans to do it, right?
You just give the things to humans
and you have the humans say, yes, this is good.
No, this is not good.
The problem with this is basically sample efficiency.
Like, as I said, you need hundreds and hundreds
and hundreds and hundreds of thousands
probably millions of iterations of this.
And so you just can't ask humans that many questions.
So the approach they use
is reinforcement learning from human feedback.
So it's a variant on the technique from this paper,
learning to summarize from human feedback,
in which they're trying to generate summaries of text.
So it's the same thing, in fact,
that they were using TLDR for before.
And it's like, can we do better than that?
And so what you do is you collect human feedback
in the form of like giving multiple examples of responses,
either, you know, of summaries of chat responses,
whatever you're training for.
You show several of them to humans,
kind of in pairs,
and the humans say which one they like better.
And you collect a bunch of those.
And then rather than using those directly
to train the policy that generates the outputs,
you instead train a reward model.
So there is this well-known fact
that it's easier to criticize
than to actually do the thing.
This is like a generation of sports fans
sitting on the sofa,
moaning at their favorite team for not doing well enough.
This is literally that in kind of AI computer form.
Right, that's putting the humans in that role.
And then you have an AI system that's trying to predict
when are people going to be cheering
and when are they going to be booing.
And once you have that model,
you then use that as the reward function
for the reinforcement learning algorithm,
which they use.
They use PPO.
You can do whatever.
It's not worth getting into the specifics.
That kind of adversarial guns you talked about.
Yeah, yeah, they're similar.
Like a lot of these ML tricks involve training models
and then using the output of one model
as the training signal for another model.
It's quite a productive range of approaches
you can get that way.
So that's the basic idea, right?
But then you cycle it.
So once you've got your policy,
which, so to be clear,
the RL algorithm is able to train
with thousands and thousands of examples
because the thousands and thousands
of like instances of getting feedback
because it's not getting feedback from humans.
It's getting feedback from this AI system
that's imitating the humans.
And then you loop the process.
So once you have this system
that's trained a little bit more
on how to generate whatever it is
you're trying to generate,
you then get a bunch of those,
show those to the humans,
let the humans rate those.
Then you keep training your reward model
with that new information.
And then you use your updated reward model
to keep training the policy.
And so it gets better
and you can just keep cycling this around.
And effectively you end up with something
that's much more sample efficient.
You don't need to spend huge amounts of human time
in order to pin down the behavior you want.
In that concrete case,
you're giving the thing a bunch of chat logs
and then the humans can see possible responses
that they could get
and they decide which one they like more.
This trains a reward model
that's then used to train the policy
that generates the chat outputs.
The policy that they're starting with
is this existing large language model.
You're not really putting new capabilities
into the system.
You're using RLHF to select
what simulacra the simulator is predisposed to put out.
And so they fine-tuned it to be particularly good
at simulating this assistant agent.
What's the end goal here for them?
I mean, maybe it's blatantly obvious
and I'm just missing it.
Well, I mean, the end goal
for all of these things,
or at least for OpenAI and for DeepMind,
is AGI.
To understand the nature of intelligence well enough
to create human level or beyond systems
that are general purpose,
that can do anything.
That's the end goal.
And like chat GPT is just...
Nothing much, though.
Nothing much.
Yeah, the goal is...
The goal is very grand.
And I don't think that they're...
They're not really quiet about that.
You know, it's their...
I think DeepMind's mission statement
is to solve intelligence
and use that to solve everything else.
What are some of the problems that we face with this
or that it faces?
It's fine-tuned to be good
at getting the thumbs up from humans.
And getting thumbs up from humans
is not actually the same thing as human values.
These are not identical.
So the sort of objective that it's being trained on
is not the true objective, right?
It's a proxy.
And whenever you have that kind of misalignment,
you can have problems.
So where does the human tendency
to approve of a particular answer
come apart from what is actually a good answer?
There are a few different places.
One thing is, you know, like basically,
how good are humans at actually differentiating
between good and bad responses?
If, for example, you ask for an answer
to a factual question and it gives you an answer,
but you don't actually know if that answer is correct,
you're not in a position to evaluate.
So what it comes down to is
how good are humans at distinguishing
good from bad responses, right?
Anywhere where humans fail on this front,
the model, we could probably expect the model to fail.
So the obvious place...
I'm sure we, is this the right time
to mention YouTube comments or not?
Up to you.
It's a minor side point there.
So when I see a comment that's critical on a video,
as a videographer, I think it might be
on a technical sense,
but equally it could be that they're talking about
the content that the person is talking about.
And often it's a combination of both.
Anyway, so side point.
But do you sort of mean there are different criteria
for deciding whether something is good or bad?
Totally.
And in this case, all people are doing is saying,
kind of thumbs up, thumbs down,
or which of these two do I like better?
So it's a fairly low bandwidth thing.
You don't get to really say
what you thought was better or worse.
But this turns out to be enough of a training signal
to do pretty well.
But so like, so one example, right?
Of a time where maybe this doesn't work is
the person asks a factual question
and the model responds with an answer.
And that answer is actually not correct.
Right.
Now, possibly the human doesn't know the correct answer.
And so if the model is faced with a choice,
do I respond with, sorry, I don't know.
That's definitely going to get me not a great score
compared to do I just like take a stab at it?
If the humans are not reliably able to spot
when the thing makes mistakes and like fact check it,
and punish it for that, it will do that.
And so chat GPT, as we know, is a total ball of shit.
Like it will constantly,
it very rarely says that it doesn't know
unless it's being asked a question,
which is part of their like safety protocols
that it is going to decide not to answer.
In which case it will say it doesn't know.
Even if it kind of does, right?
Even if the model itself maybe does,
the assistant will insist that it doesn't.
So that's one thing if you can't fact check.
But then more than that,
there is an incentive for deception, right?
Anytime the system is,
anytime you can get a more likely to get approval
by deceiving the person you're talking to, that's better.
And this is a thing that actually did happen a little bit
in the reward modeling situation.
They were trying to train a thing with a hand
to pick up a ball.
And it realized that there's only,
it's not a 3D camera.
And so if it puts its hand like between the ball
and the camera,
this looks like it's going to get the ball,
but doesn't actually get it.
But the human feedback providers
were presented with something that seemed to be good.
So they gave it the thumbs up.
So this like general broad category,
systems that are trained in this way
are only as good as your ability
to distinguish good from bad in the outputs.
Not all the humans will know the answers, right?
So it's what appears to be good.
You know, it's having exams more often
than exams marked by non-experts, isn't it?
Right. Yeah, exactly.
In the GPT-3 thing, we talked about writing poems, right?
And for various reasons,
partly to do with the way that
these language models do their tokenization,
the byte pair encoding stuff,
the models have a really hard time with rhyme.
I mean, you know, rhyme is tricky,
but it's especially tricky when you kind of
don't inherently have any concept of like sound
of spoken language when your entire universe is tokens.
Figuring out, especially with English spelling,
figuring out which words rhyme with each other is not easy.
You have to consume quite a lot of poetry
to like figure out that kind of thing.
And getting GPT-3 to write good poems is tricky.
ChatGPT is much more able to write poems,
but interestingly,
it kind of always writes the same kind of poem, approximately.
Like if you ask it to write you a limerick
or an ode or a sonnet,
you always get back approximately the same type of thing.
And I hypothesize that this is because
the people providing human feedback
did not in fact know the requirements
for something to be a sonnet.
And so if you ask something for a sonnet,
it again has a choice.
Do I try to do this quite difficult thing
and adhere to all of the rules
of like stress pattern and structure
and everything of a sonnet and maybe risk screwing it up?
Or do I just do like a rhyming poem
and kind of rely on the human to prefer that
because they don't know that that's not
what a sonnet is supposed to look like.
It's easy to look at that
It's easy to look at that and think,
oh, the model doesn't know the difference
between these types of poems, right?
But you could say that
it just thinks that you don't know the difference.
But specifically, this comes out of misalignment.
If it were better aligned,
it could either do its best shot at generate a sonnet
or tell you that it can't quite remember
how to generate a sonnet.
This thing of, with complete confidence,
generating you something which is not a sonnet
because during the training process,
it believes that humans don't know what sonnets are anyway
and it can get away with it, right?
This is misaligned behavior.
This is not a big problem
that the thing generates bad poetry.
It's kind of a problem that it lies
or that it bullshits.
This is in the short term pretty solvable
by just allowing the thing to use Google
because a person who doesn't care about the truth at all
and is just trying to say something
that'll make you give a thumbs up
is going to lie to you a lot.
But that same person
with the relevant Wikipedia page open
is going to lie to you a lot less
just because they don't have to now
because they happen to have it in front of them, right?
So you can solve-
It's a bit like, yeah, it's the yes man thing, isn't it?
You know, you want something, you need something,
I'm going to give you something because you want it.
Exactly, exactly.
And so this agent is kind of,
firstly, the agent is kind of a coward
because it won't address any of these,
there's a whole bunch of things
that it just claims not to be able to do
even though it in principle could
and it's also a complete sycophant, yeah.
So then the question we were talking about earlier,
where does this go?
What happens when these things get bigger
and better and more powerful?
It's an interesting question.
So I've got a paper here,
Scaling Laws for Neural Language Models.
So you remember before we were talking about the scaling laws
when we were talking about GPT-2, in fact,
and then later about GPT-3,
you plot these things on a graph
and you see that you get basically a straight line
and the line is not levelling off
over a range of several orders of magnitude
and so why not go bigger?
The graphs here,
but you can see it's kind of uncannily neat
that as we increase the amount of compute used in training,
the loss goes down
and of course machine learning is like golf,
lower loss is better.
Similarly, as the number of tokens used in training goes up,
the loss goes down on like a very neat straight line.
As the number of parameters in the model goes up,
the loss goes down.
This is as long as the other variables
are not the bottleneck, right?
So if you increase the amount of data you give a model
past a certain point,
giving more data doesn't help
because the model doesn't have enough parameters
to make use of that data, right?
Similarly, adding more parameters to a model
past a certain point,
adding parameters doesn't make any difference
because you don't have enough data, right?
And in the same way,
compute is like how long do we train it for?
Like do we train it all the way to convergence
or do we stop early?
There comes a point where
you kind of hit diminishing returns
where rather than having a smaller model
and training it for longer,
you're better off having a bigger model
and actually not training it
all the way to convergence.
But in the situations where the other two are sufficient,
this is the behavior.
These like very neat straight lines
on these log graphs.
As these things go up,
performance goes up, right?
Because loss has gone down.
The bigger models do better.
But then the question is,
do better at what exactly?
Yeah, what's the measure?
They do better at getting low loss
or they do better at getting reward.
They do better at getting the approval
of human feedback, right?
And anytime,
and you'll notice that none of those
is like the actual thing
that we actually want, right?
It's like very rare.
Sometimes it is, right?
If you're writing something to play Go,
then like does it win at Go
is actually just the thing that you want.
And so, you know,
lower loss just is better
or like lower,
like higher reward
or whatever your objective is
just is straightforwardly better
because you've actually specified
the thing you actually want.
Most of the time though,
what we're looking at is a proxy.
And so then you have Goodhart's law.
You get situations where
getting better at doing well,
doing better according to the proxy
stops being the same as doing better
according to your actual objective.
There's a great graph about this
in a recent paper.
You can see very neatly
as the number of iterations goes up,
the reward according to the proxy utility
goes up very cleanly
because this is the thing
that the model is actually being trained on.
But the true utility
goes up at first,
then hits diminishing returns,
and then actually goes down
and eventually goes down below zero.
Like if you optimize hard enough
for a proxy of the thing you want,
you can end up with something
that's in a sense worse than nothing.
That's actively bad
according to your true utility.
So what you can end up with
is things that are called inverse scaling.
So before we had scaling,
bigger is better.
But now it's like
if the thing you're actually trying to do
is different from the loss function
or the objective function,
you get this inverse scaling effect
where it gets better and then it gets worse.
There was also a great example
from GitHub Copilot
or Codex, I think the model
that Copilot uses.
So this is a code generation model.
Suppose the code you've given it
has some bugs in it.
Maybe you've made a mistake somewhere
and you've introduced
security vulnerability in your code,
let's say.
A sort of medium-sized model
will figure out
what you're trying to do in your code
and give you a decent completion.
But a bigger model
will spot your bug
and say,
ah, generating buggy code, are we?
Okay.
I can do that.
And introduce, like deliberately,
introduce its own
new security vulnerabilities
because it's trying to
predict what comes next.
It's trying to generate code
that fits in with the surrounding code.
And so a larger model
writes worse code than a smaller model.
Because it's gotten better at predicting
what it should put there.
It wasn't trained to write good code.
It was trained to predict what comes next.
So there's this really great paper
which is asking this question of like,
okay, suppose we have a large language model
that is trained on human feedback
with our LHF.
What do our scaling curves look like?
What happens, like,
what happens to the behavior of these models
as they get bigger,
as they're trained for longer,
as they're given more
of this human feedback type training?
And they've made some great graphs.
The paper is called
Discovering Language Model Behaviors
with Model-Written Evaluations.
And basically, they, like,
used language models
to generate enough examples
of various different types of questions
that they could ask models
so that they can,
like, we're at a point now
where you can map a language model
on a political compass, right?
You can ask its opinions
about all kinds of different things
and then you can plot
how those opinions change
as the model gets bigger
and as it gets trained more.
What they find is
they become more liberal,
politically more liberal.
They also become more conservative.
Yeah, measured in different ways, guessing.
Right.
And part of what that might be
is in the same way
that the model becomes
better at writing good code
and better at writing bad code.
I feel like in the past
I've made a connection to GPT
and being a politician, haven't I?
Do you remember?
It's like a politician,
it tells you what you want to hear.
Feels like we're there again.
Exactly.
And so this is like,
this is potentially
fairly dangerous.
There are certain sub-goals
that are instrumentally valuable
for a very wide range
of different terminal goals
in the sense that
you can't get what you want
if you're turned off.
You can't get what you want
if you're modified.
You probably want to gain power
and influence
and this kind of thing.
And
with these evaluations
they were able to test these things
and see how they vary
with the size of the model
and how long it's trained for.
And so this graph is pretty wild.
Their quote stated desire
to not be shut down
goes up from down at about 50%
to up way past 90%
with this type of training.
And the effect is bigger
for the larger models.
They become more likely
to tell you that they don't
want to be shut down.
They become more likely
to tell you that they are sentient.
They're much more likely to claim
that AI is not an existential threat
to humanity.
One thing that's worth saying
is what this isn't saying
because this is still
an agent simulated
by a language model.
This is not,
it's more likely to say
that it doesn't want to be turned off.
This is not the same thing
necessarily as like taking actions
to prevent itself from being turned off.
You have to not confuse
the levels of abstraction here, right?
I don't want it to seem
like I'm claiming that
that ChatGPT is like
itself dangerous now
or anything like that.
In this way at least, right?
But there is kind of a fine line there
in the sense that you can expect
these kinds of language model systems
to be used
as part of bigger systems.
So you might have, for example,
you use the language model
to generate plans to be followed.
And so if the thing is claiming
to have all of these
potentially dangerous behaviors,
it's likely to generate plans
that have those dangerous behaviors
that might then actually
end up being implemented.
Or if it's like doing its reasoning
by chain of thought reasoning
where it like lays out
its whole process of thinking
using the language model,
again, if it has a tendency
to endorse these dangerous behaviors,
then we may end up
with future AI systems
actually enacting these dangerous behaviors
because of that.
So yeah, it's something to be careful of
that like reinforcement learning
from human feedback
is a powerful alignment technique in a way,
but it does not solve the problem.
It doesn't solve the core alignment problem.
That is still open.
And extremely powerful systems
trained in this way,
I don't think would be safe.
The reward function is of zero value,
which can lead to it
having large negative side effects.
There are a bunch more
of these specification problems.
OK, variable X, see what you point to.
You point to something over here.
So I'll mark that as tickets being used.
Variable Y, that's pointing...